<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>No præexistence, or, A brief dissertation against the hypothesis of humane souls, living in a state antecedaneous to this by E.W. ...</title>
            <author>E. W. (Edward Warren)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67678</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12145233</idno>
  <idno type="VID">54939</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961004</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12145233</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 905:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>No præexistence, or, A brief dissertation against the hypothesis of humane souls, living in a state antecedaneous to this by E.W. ...</title>
                  <author>E. W. (Edward Warren)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Samuel Thomson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Pre-existence.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54939:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54939:1"/>
            <p>NO PRAEEXISTENCE. OR A Brief Dissertation Against The HYPOTHESIS OF Humane SOULS, Living in a State <hi>Antecedaneous</hi> to This.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. W.</hi> A. M.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Coloss. 2. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Thomson</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bishops-Head</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M DC LX VII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54939:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54939:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ventured thus Publiquely to ingage against <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> I presume not a few will be apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Reason of it: And though to satisfie the inquisitive in this Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, be not very materiate; yet because it will stand me but in little trouble, I shall not refuse the doing it.</p>
            <p>The Principal cause then, of my clashing thus open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> was for that (in my apprehension) it seemed <hi>Eccentrick</hi> unto <hi>Verity,</hi> and I could never deem it any thing else but a figment and an Error; and I loved not to see, what I reputed a fable and Imposture, Travel so confidently through the World, and every where vaunt it self for a genuine Truth, and
<pb facs="tcp:54939:3"/> exact the honour and respect, and Challenge the Credit and assent, which is due alone to veracious Principles; but must needs be questioning the Legitimacy thereof, and lifting up the Skirts of its painted Vail to shew it was a counterfeit. As many bog and sturdy <hi>Mendicants,</hi> who pretend themselves to be Persons of Quality, upon strict Examination are found but dissembling Vagrants; so I was half perswaded, that if this Opinion, which Apes and Personates the Generosity of Truth, were throughly sifted, it would appear no better than a Cheat and Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy: And something I have done to prove it such.</p>
            <p>Tis confest I might have been as Prudent, if I had kept these Lines in secret, and never permitted them to have seen the Light, unless of those Flames which should have Consumed them: But being tempted a little to make them Publique, it was my Weaknes to be overcome; and now it is too late to Repent, it is my Wisest Course to Resolve I will not.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54939:3"/>
            <head>NO <hi>PRAEEXISTENCE,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Souls</hi> first emergencie out of nothing, <hi>doubtfull,</hi> and <hi>incognoscible.</hi> 2. Three different Conjectures about it. 3. The Authors method in discoursing against <hi>Praeex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence.</hi> 4. The <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of it stated, and explained.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst the dubious Theories, so hotly disputed by the Sophies of the World, the <hi>time</hi> of humane Souls production, is not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est: That they had a beginning, is a Truth of Mathematical certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and demonstrable by the soundest reasons; but when they were educed out of non entitie, is a Probleme though fiercely debated, not satisfactorily resolved; nor indeed (considering the darkness, and perplexity of it,) can we hope to have it cleared up
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54939:4"/> to our apprehensions in this life, by the most painfull lucubrations; the head of slimy <hi>Nile</hi> is not so recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and occult, nor of half so difficult investigation, as the time of Souls first <hi>immigration</hi> into being; such crass and pitchy Clouds of secrecie obnubilate and hide it, that the most sagacious and quick-sighted mortal (have he never such <hi>Lyncean</hi> eyes) must not pretend to penetrate them, and descrie the veiled mysterie; so that unless it be revealed by a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an audible voice from heaven, or proclaimed by a winged Herald, from the Pallace of the great JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH; we must utterly despair of knowing it, till death shall amplifie our science, and make us more intelligent; this the profoundest of the <hi>Latin Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gists</hi> was sensible of; and therefore having wearied himself, in exploring the time, when Souls first issued into life, he resign'd his fruitless disquisitions, and was content to be a Sceptick in reference to the theorem; concluding that as understanding it, was no essential unto happiness; so ignorance of it, would infer no danger. <hi>Non est periculum si origo animae lateat, dum redemptio clareat,</hi> St. <hi>Aug. Epist.</hi> 157.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But though the time of our Souls first investi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with life and being, cannot precisely be desir'd by any, yet it is fairly conjectured at by divers.</p>
               <p>Some hold the Souls of men, are of a <hi>later existence</hi> than their bodies; and that those being first made fit for organization, they are afterwards, at once created and infus'd into them; according to that known tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; <hi>anima creando infunditur, &amp; infundendo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others opine they are <hi>coaetaneous</hi> with these fleshly machins, and conceive that together with them, they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54939:4"/> are propagated by certain seminal excrescencies, and prolifique emanations, derived from the Parents Souls; and that they are thus produced by way of fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, by trifling and obstreperous arguments, they would prove unto the credulous.</p>
               <p>Others fetch their rise a great deal higher, and give their origin a far earlier date, they make them <hi>coaeval</hi> with the Angels, and tell us they were once copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with them in their glories; till unfortunately sliding from the aethereall Paradise, they turn'd poor Pilgrims upon earth; and thus the <hi>Platonists</hi> rant it, bearing the World in hand, that their essences did not then commence, when they became incarnate, and by invisible Fetters were chained to these bulks of flesh; but that they were born together with the Universe, and had spent some Ages, in the purer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable parts thereof, before they stoop'd to visit, these obscure and duskie Regions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This is that Romantick dogmatism we are to enquire into; and to the end its precariousness, and falsitie, may the better be detected, I shall First, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound and explicate the <hi>Hypothesis</hi> it self; Secondly, refell the chiefest <hi>Arguments,</hi> alledged in confirmation of it; and Thirdly, object the most weighty <hi>Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> against it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As to the <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> it runs thus; that the Souls of men, did not then first sallie forth from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Abyss of nothing, when they began to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate these lumps of Clay, and were confined to their earthly Tenements; but existed long before in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and blessed state, constipated with various privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and beset on all sides with unparalleld felicity, till at length being cloyed with the Joyes of Heaven,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54939:5"/> they longed for corporeal pleasures; and did not only give way to the soft and gentler vibrations of them, and imbibe them in allowed measures, and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but grew inordinate admirers of them, and with too lax desires, and unbridled appetites, rioted on their luscious suavities, to a rash transilience of the bounds of temperance; and this was it which made them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable; their immoderate ingurgitation of animal complacencies, drinking deep of that Circean, and intoxicative Cup, they took a surfet, fell sick, and died to their Caelestial happiness; the poisonous steams which rose from that accursed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they had too frankely drunk of, soon struck them with a fatall diz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziness, and made them topple from their primaeval glory, into a lower and less happy station; for having stain'd their spotless Essences, by the love and practice of impure delights, a great disharmony befell their nature; their vital aptitude to their first refined ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicles, forthwith decayed; their vigorous reason was bound up and stupefi'd, and they themselves made quite incapable of an aethereal life: And being thus incapacitated to live above, and driven to relinquish their native habitation; they wandred in the search of courser matter, which might make them bodies congruous to their polluted beings: Now as many of these naked vagrants (so they may be call'd, being stripped of their Caelestial bodies) as chanced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend within the <hi>Atmosphere</hi> of this Terrestrial globe; and still continued to degenerate, soking themselves in sensuality, are supposed in tract of time, to lose the use of their reason, and then of their senses too; which for a time (while the rational powers lie cramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and benummed with a deadly sopor) are thought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54939:5"/> to concern themselves in action, till at last being tir'd out, with violent and assiduous exercise, they likewise fall asleep, leaving the forlorn, and drowzy Souls, to the conduct of the <hi>Spirit of Nature;</hi> and this is so much their friend, that it will not permit them to lodge for ever in a state of silence; but as oft as it meets with fit opportunities, clasping hold of their <hi>plastick</hi> parts, which are invigorated immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the consopition of the sensual faculties; crouds them into carnal bodies, and intombs the half dead Creatures, in these living Sepulchres: And this their tragical detrusion into earthly vehicles, like bifront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Janus,</hi> wears a double aspect; for as it may be reckoned a severe correction of their immortallities, in the praeexistent state; so it may be counted a signal favour to them; for hereby they are licens'd to try their fortunes in this inferiour World, and to return from whence they fell, if they industriously strive to do it.</p>
               <p>Thus have I briefly depainted the <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>existence,</hi> and I think in its genuine colours, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions; I shall now dip my Pencill again, and go on to pourtray the principal <hi>Arguments,</hi> urged to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticate it; subnecting respective <hi>confutations</hi> to each of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54939:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The first Argument for Praeexistence, drawn from the nature of <hi>Divine Goodness.</hi> 2. GODS <hi>Goodness</hi> though infinite, not alwayes Active of what is <hi>best,</hi> because subject to the Regiment of his <hi>Will.</hi> 3. This subjection proved from Scripture. 4. From the late Creation of the World; 5. And the restriction of the Law, to the Jewish Nation. 6. From the serotinous Advent of CHRIST. 7. The Perpetuity of Hell. 8. And the lapse of Humane Souls, if they Praeexisted.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey that present the world with heterodoxes, and would have their specious errors, pass for sacred and infallible Truths; dress them up as well as they can, in the habit of Verity, how abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous soever they be from it; and are very anxious to confirm their vafrous Doctrine, by fucous or coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reasons; which may be as so many Statumina or sure fulciments, to sustain and shore up its ruent cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; and here the <hi>Praeexistentiaries</hi> are no whit behind hand; for the wild Tenet they assert, they strive to establish by several Allegations; to encounter and enervate which is now my Province.</p>
               <p>The First then, and in truth the strongest Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54939:6"/> they press to militate in their quarrell, and maintain their opinion, is the Soveraign and redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <hi>Goodness</hi> of the ALMIGHTY, which they hold is strictly obliged by its own nature, ever to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish those things that are <hi>best;</hi> and to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it self to all Creatures, in measures adaequate to their largest dimensions, and capacities: Now the Souls of men, being capable of existence, long before they were vested with this gross corporeity; and it being best for them to have existed, long before that time; hence it inevitably follows, that they did so.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That GOD is infinitely Good; is a position <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> as true as himself, nor can he that is furnisht with the reason of a man, offer to dispute it; for he is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Prince and self originated Good: <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> constitutes his very Deity, making him to be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; for could he be arrayed with all his other Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, separate and abstract from this; they would be so far from denominating him a GOD, that he would be but a prodigious Feind, and plenipotenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Devil: 'Tis Goodness that is the Head and Glory of His perfect Essence; and therefore when <hi>Moses</hi> importuned him for a Vision of his Glory, he ingaged <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 19.</note> to display his <hi>Goodness</hi> to him: But granting him to be thus transcendently and Essentially GOOD; yet that he must therefore be fatally necessitated, to do alwayes the best things; is no natural deduction from the Concession; no more than it is to averr, he must alwayes be working the most stupendious Miracles, because he is omnipotent; indeed by reason of the perfection of his Goodness, he can do nothing save what is Good; and by vertue of the Infinity of the same, it is as natural to him to shed abroad his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54939:7"/> as it is to the Sun to ray forth his light, or the Fire to disfuse its heat; but that he alwayes does what is best, and so can do no more good than he actually does, is hugely improbable; for it is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to any indifferent understanding, that there is some thing in GOD, which in many cases restrains the activity of his Goodness, and suspends its effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of divers things, that otherwise might be done, and if done would be incomparably good; and this coercive principle is undoubtedly his <hi>Will:</hi> For these two; the <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> of GOD, have a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and reciprocal agency upon each other; and as his Goodness so far influenceth the Praedominance of his Will, as to incline it alwayes to noble Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; so his Will again so far controlls the exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his Goodness, as to select the enterprises, in compleating of which (praetermitting all others, though perhaps more excellent) it shall expend it self. And this Supremacy of the Will, over the Goodness of the Divine Nature, may be made out, both by <hi>Scripture,</hi> and other forcible <hi>Evidences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. For to this agrees that Paragraph of the <hi>Psalmist, Psal. 135. 6. Whatsoever the</hi> LORD <hi>pleased, that did he in Heaven, and in Earth, in the Seas, and all Deep places:</hi> Not those things that were simply, and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively best in themselves, were brought to pass; but those that he pleased; such as his Wisdom approved, and his Will appointed to be done: And parallel to this, we find another Text, St. <hi>Matt. 20. 15. Is it not lawfull for me, to do what I will with mine own?</hi> A plain intimation, that the exertions of GODS Goodness, are not Physical and necessary; but spontaneous and arbitrary; and that he hath power to dispence, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54939:7"/> with-hold, to dilate or contract the gratuitous colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his favour, as he thinks meet; and very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable it is, that at the same time when he owned Goodness for the <hi>Glory</hi> of his nature unto <hi>Moses,</hi> he proclaimed of himself; <hi>I will be gracious, to whom I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 19.</note>
                  <hi>will be gracious.</hi> Thereby assuring us, that the exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions of his Goodness, are entirely dependant on his Will; and that notwithstanding he is infinitely Good, he can express his benevolence as he thinketh fit; and is not bound alwayes to apportion the effusions of it, to the fullest amplitude, and capaciousness of created Recipients (which in reference to them is best) but may ampliate, or abate the same, according to his own beneplaciture.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This is farther indigitated, by the <hi>late production of the World:</hi> For were it necessary for GOD to do alwayes what is best, and not free for him to do what he will; how comes it to pass that the World is not yet (according to usual computation) full Seven thousand years old, whereas it might have stood as many Ages? If any to wade the dint of this objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, shall fix its initial period higher, and perswade that the story of the Creation, described by <hi>Moses</hi> in the beginning of his Pentateuch, relates only to the sublimary World, and this terrestrial Planet, which was then first made habitable and peopled; but that the great Universe was longer liv'd, and must have its Nativity calculated by an earlier Epoch: This will signifie very little; for still the Argument will be the same; and admitting the Universe were Created ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so soon, yet the same question will recurr; why was it not produced sooner? For since the earliest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence we can assign it, is best for it; if it be fatal to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54939:8"/> GOD'S Goodness, to do alwayes that which is best; why did this glorious frame of bodies, and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genous Creatures extant in the same, sleep so long in the Lap of nothing, before they were awakened into being? Certainly if <hi>Ens</hi> and <hi>Bonum</hi> be convertibles, and if it be good to <hi>be;</hi> then it is better that the Machin of the World (so omnimodously august and splended, and so pregnant with accomplisht pulchritude and harmony,) and the goodly beings therein contained, (which are as so many <hi>Ectypa,</hi> dim shadows, and dark resemblances of GOD'S Archetypal perfections, as stamped with lively signatures of his Attributes) it is better I say, that these should <hi>be,</hi> than <hi>not be;</hi> and if this Position be true of them now, it was as true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them Millions of ages before they were: Why therefore did they not then actually exist? and, why did that Ideal faecundity, (presumed to lodge in the Divine Intellect,) forbear so long to sprout forth, and flourish into real Entities? Nothing could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pead this, but the dominion of GOD'S Will over his Goodness, and the power it hath to check and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain the diffusiveness of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And that it hath such a power, is farther appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the <hi>patefaction of the Law, but to one single People, namely the Jews:</hi> For when the Majesty of Heaven, stoopt to the Paedagogy of Mortals, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to imbue their minds, with the principles of Mortallity, and to instill into them an excellent Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; (such was the Law delivered in <hi>Sinai,</hi> though the duties of it were circumstantiated with servile Rites, and a discipline operous and irksome,) he did not congregrate the whole Posterity of <hi>Adam</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reveal his Will promiscuously to them all,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54939:8"/> and indite his statutes for them in their respective Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, that so they might understand and keep them; but he withdrew into the unfrequented Desert of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> and there in an obscure place, remote from the notices of the World, by the praeconization of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, he published his holy Edicts to a few thousands of People, the afflicted progeny of <hi>Heber.</hi> Now I appeal to any competent Judge; if it had not been infinitely better, that GOD should have apertly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penst his Ordinances to all mankind, and have sealed the truth and excellence of them, by mirificous tokens from above, so that they could not but have accepted them, for the Canon of their lives; than to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them only unto <hi>Israel,</hi> in so private and clancu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar a manner: 'Tis confest, they were impowred to Proselite those of all Nations, that would conform to their <hi>Law;</hi> and to adopt them into a participation of their Religious Priviledges: But though this was a mercy unto Aliens and Exoticks, yet nothing compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to what the publication of the Law to them would have been: For whereas by this contrivance, very few <hi>Gentiles</hi> were won from their Ethmiscisme, to an association in the <hi>Jewish</hi> mode of Worship; had the <hi>Law</hi> been openly proclaimed to them, they would all ('tis like) have received it with as much alacrity, and observed it with as great fidelity, as ever the claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and ficcle <hi>Hebrews</hi> did; for as many as should have been Auditors, and spectators of its delivery, being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or instructed from heaven, must needs have yielded; if not a prompt obedience to its injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, yet an unanimous assent to the equity and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness of the same: And they hereby recommending them to their Children; and they again to theirs, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54939:9"/> so on successively: The whole World would have been generally tenacious of, and many every where obsequious to, those venerable Institutes; till the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral part of them had been reinforced, and the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial antiquated by the induction of a better oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Since therefore the Law, had it been exhibited to all Nations, would probably have found a free and Universal reception, and have proved of singular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to them; the divine Goodness, were it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes necessarily effective of the <hi>best things;</hi> should not have cloistered it up in the Custody of a few <hi>Tribes,</hi> but rather have openly commonstrated it, to all the Families of the Earth; and proposed it with awakening pomp and awfull solemnities, to their strictest observation. But now that this was not done; is to be imputed solely to GOD'S Will, which laid a restraint upon his Goodness in the case; and made him partial in communicating his mind unto his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; causing him to choose the <hi>Jewish</hi> Congregation, for the depositary of his <hi>Oracles,</hi> though with the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terition of the whole World besides; nor can their assumption into that Prerogative, be deemed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of any thing else but GOD'S free Will, which inclined his Goodness to Elect them, to such an eximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mercy; they had nothing to condecorate, and set them off in his sight more than others: No inherent worth or peculiar merit, that might attract this signal favour, (or if in point of Vertue they did surpass their neighbours, GOD gave them that transcendency, and if he had <hi>will'd</hi> it, all people should have been their Peers; and therefore his pleasure, here checkt his Goodness also, and made the difference) only <hi>he loved them (Deut.</hi> 7.) and for that cause, chose them to such
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54939:9"/> an eminent blessing; and the reason why other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons shared not in it is, because he loved them not so well; and he loved them not so well, because he <hi>would</hi> not: His <hi>Will</hi> obstructed the effluxes of his Goodness towards them, in such a rare instance of mercy, as the alarming them out of their Gentilism, by the ebucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his Counsels to them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Another Argument of the Sovoraignty of GOD'S Will, over his Goodness; is his <hi>timeing the Messiah's Nativity,</hi> and bringing it to pass not in the Worlds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, or adolescence, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(Heb.</hi> 1. 1.) In its declining Age or grandaevity; but how this should be <hi>best,</hi> and most conducent to the happiness of Mankind, is to me a Mystery; for before CHRIST the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Morning-Starr,</hi> arose in the Haemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphere of this present World; we know a palpable darkness over-spread the greatest part of it; a piceous Cloud of Error and Ignorance circumtected it; and where the beams of divine Truth shone brightest, they yielded but a kind of <hi>diluculum,</hi> a faint and glimmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light: To throw abroad the open day, was to be his work, who is <hi>the Sun of Righteousness.</hi> Herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted a chief part of his <hi>Prophetick Office,</hi> in that he was to replenish the Earth with a pure knowledge, and the glorious displaies of Evangelical verities; in that he was to be the Expositor of his Fathers Will, and the Dispenser of his mind, and the great <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or wise Interpreter of Heavens Secrets; and therefore he is Stiled <hi>the Counseller, of the World, the Word, the Way and the Truth, the great Prophet,</hi> and the like. Now the World being inveloped with caligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous spissitudes, before the Incarnation of CHRIST; and these dense opacities, being not to be dispelled till
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54939:10"/> his coming; because it was reserved for him as a principal piece of his <hi>Prophetick function</hi> (as I have noted) to lighten the benighted World, and irradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the minds of men with his luminous Doctrines: Who that is Master of his own reason, will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it had been much better, that the Son of GOD had been incarnate <hi>sooner,</hi> and had assumed an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane body in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Ages; that so being fitted to converse with men, he might have dictated that perfect Law unto them; the publishing of which was one main end of his exinanition, as the trite diverb goes, <hi>bis dat, qui cito dat,</hi> he duplicates his bounty, that imparts it speedily: Which if it hath any alliance with Truth, fairly intimates that if GOD had acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated the Birth of his Son, and dispensed his Gospel in the Worlds Juvenility; he should thereby have added, considerably to the Magnitude of the benefit, and inhanced the mercy to an high pitch of optimacy, which was quite lost by its tedious dilation, and tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous accomplishment. And since GOD might thus have ingrandized the blessing of the Gospel, by an earlier mission of his <hi>Son</hi> to Preach the same; and so have amplified the signal mercy of our LORD'S Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, but did not; hence it is evident, that his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in exerting it self, is not tied to observe the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genists</hi> rule, of <hi>doing alwayes what is best;</hi> but rather that it acts perpetually, in an even and harmonical compliance with the divine Will; and diffuseth it self in larger or lesser proportions, as that permits or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: Nor know I what could prorogue and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the appearance of CHRIST, till within these Seventeen hundred years; except GOD'S volition of it, and the praevalence of his Will above his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54939:10"/> Goodness, determining it should be no sooner.</p>
               <p>If it be urged as a necessary <hi>Remora</hi> of his Advent, that there were sundry Praedictions, indigitating and pointing out the time of his coming; and therefore he was bound to step into the World, just when he did, that these might not be falsifyed and cluded. It may be Answered; that these Prophecies were Penned, long after the time of our SAVIOUR'S Incarnation, was pitcht upon and prefixed: And being thus conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to GOD'S immutable designation, of that happy juncture of time, in which his Son was to be revealed: They cannot properly be said to prevent and stave it off, but only to praemonstrate it. As an Astronomers praedicting an Eclypse to happen the next year, is no cause why it does not fall out before; but only a Prognostication of the futurity of the accident, which would have been at the same time, though he had never fore-shown it. So the praenunciations of our REDEEMER'S Birth, were not the cause why it was no sooner, but only praeindications of its future completion, which happened no whit the later for these: For GOD first punctually defined when his Nativity should be; and then Prophesied of it, adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his praedictions to a just coincidence with it: So that though the Messiah could not possibly visit the World sooner, than it was foretold he should; because these Prophecies were made to relate, to the real time of his Advent; yet they were not causal of his so long demurre, forasmuch as they were inspired and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, long after the period of his blessed Birth, was stated and fore-ordained by omniscient Providence.</p>
               <p>But admit it were yielded, that CHRIST de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired his profection from the Father meerly upon the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54939:11"/> account of these Praedictions, and that for the verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them, he was Incarnate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20.) in these <hi>last times:</hi> Yet still his <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical</hi> absence, will nevertheless be imputed wholly to the divine Will, because it extended these praemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Advent so far, and drew them out to such a length; whereas it might as well have limited them to a shorter tract of time, and made the complement of them <hi>Synchronal</hi> with the Birth of JESUS, (so that it need not have clashed with Heavens veracity) though it had anticipated that, which proved the time of its event by many Ages.</p>
               <p>To sum up all in a few words: It had been best for the Sons of men, that the LORD JESUS should have been manifested much sooner than he was; and therefore the detainment of him (procured only by the divine Will) clearly evinceth, that the Goodness of GOD acts subordinately to his Will; and not according to its own infinite plenitude and fertility: For then the rich and Cardinal mercy of CHRIST'S Incarnation, should have been consummated sooner, a speedier completion of it, being most consonous to the nature of the Divine bounty, if it alwayes does what is best.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A farther confirmation yet of this Truth; that the Will of GOD presides over his Goodness, so that it cannot alwayes do what is best; may be bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from <hi>the perpetuity of Hell,</hi> and the intermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness of those tortures, which after this life, shall incessantly vex the Impious: For had the penalties of mens sins here, been rated by pure Goodness, free and uncontrolled by any other Principle; it is not proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they should have been mulcted by an eternal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54939:11"/> calamity, the oblectations of them being so transient and fugitive: But since <hi>de facto,</hi> it is so; this convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly argues that the Goodness of GOD was not left to it self in meting out the punitive sorrows of delinquent Spirits; but by the authority of his Will, was lead to a permission of the extreamest severities upon them, and made to give way to their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal sufferings. This black and ruefull Phaenomenon of Providence, so plunged the great <hi>Origen,</hi> and seemed so very contradictious, and irreconcileable to that his doctrine, of GOD'S doing ever what is best; with the same necessity that a voracious Fire burns up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected combustibles; that to make it the more verisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milous and tenable, he was fain to broach that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous error, touching the temporariness of damnation; and to teach that the infernal miseries are not infinite, but after the taedious revolution of indefinite Ages, shall expire and have an end; that the torments of Hell are Cathartical, and when they have once wrought a thorow defaecation, of the excrutiated Patients; they shall all be reprieved from their igne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prisons, and rescued from that fiery vengance which involves them, into an anodynous and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition: From which false notion of Hell, 'tis like that confus'd and broken fansie of the pur blind <hi>Gentiles</hi> sprung up; who dreamt that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or wofull conflagration, which at the Worlds Catastro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe, shall betide <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, false and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull men; shall be only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to refine and purge them from their dross and faeculence, and by an exesion of their contracted guiltiness, to reduce them to a niveous innocence: But that the Penances of Reprobates are endless, I shall ever thus perswade
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54939:12"/> my self; either the torments of Hell are eternal, or the felicities of Heaven are but temporary (which I am sure they shall never be) for the very same word that is used to express the permanence of the one, measures out the continuance of the other; and if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, denotes <hi>everlasting Life,</hi> a blessedness that <note place="margin">Mat. 25. ult.</note> shall never end; what can <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (in the same verse) signifie, but <hi>perpetual Punishment,</hi> a misery that shall never cease?</p>
               <p>Now the main foundation upon which the presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Hypothesis, of Hells temporariness is erected, is this; <hi>That GOD in all punishments inflicted on his Creatures, aims at nothing but their reformation;</hi> and therefore will only chastise their improbities in Hell, till they become better, and then release them: And since this is the chief Basis of the opinion, it will not be amiss a little to undermine it, in order to subvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the superstructed error; especially seeing it will require no great pains to do it; for it is so weak and lubricous, that it totters of its own accord, and is ready to reel without a push; to set it going therefore, I shall bestow one upon it.</p>
               <p>That GOD in chastening offendents, alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs their emendation, is palpably false; for many times he cuts them off in the midst of their crimes, by a surrepticious death; and the chastisement depriving them of all opportunities and means of amendment, consequently prevents the thing it self: But were it granted that all the punishment of criminals here, is intended to reform them; yet it does not follow from hence, that this shall be the scope of it hereafter: For between Hellish and Terrestrial penalties, there is as great difference, as betwixt ordinary Correction,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54939:12"/> and capital Execution: Correction (tis confest) is used purposely to better Malefactors, and reclaim them from their exorbitancies. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (sayes the <hi>Theologer)</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <note place="margin">Clem. Alex. Paedag. lib. 3.</note> But capital Execution is never destin'd to that end; it does not assist at all towards well doing for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but is only a sad recompence for evill actions already past. In like manner there are several Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments let fall upon the impious in this life; that are meerly corrective and curative, to castigate and deter them from illicit things, and so stimulate and spur them on, to the prosecution of nobler interests; but the torments of Hell are purely executive and destructive, (as I may say) and will be so far from meliorating those that feel them, that they will rather conduce to their pejoration; for the exquisite <hi>Acuteness,</hi> and deadly anguish of them will be such, that it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to rage and swell, with anger and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; to fret and fume against the Providence of GOD, and to curse and blaspheme the Majesty of Heaven for afflicting them; and so will sink them lower, and Chain them faster into that sulphureous Lake, and flaming Dungeon, rather than any way capacitate them for deliverance: We are much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived if we think accursed Spirits, are made of such <hi>fusile</hi> Metal, as by the longest abode in the heat of Hell, to be melted into obedience unto GOD. No, the longer they burn, the more obdurate they will grow; and their acerbous miseries running parallel with their everlasting incorrigibleness, shall be a stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing testimony of this Truth, that the Great GOD does not alwayes do what is best, but sometimes what he will.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54939:13"/>8. But in the last place, to come closer to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. If GOD'S Goodness be not under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Will, but does alwayes what is best; why did it not <hi>perpetuate the station of Praeexistent Souls,</hi> and hinder us (if ever we were happy in a sublimer state) from lapsing into these Regions of Sin and Death? If it be Answered that GOD could not prevent this, because the nature of men was from the beginning mutable, and if they would wilfully ruine themselves (a capacity of doing it being complicated with their nature) GOD could no way help it. I inquire then why GOD did not out of his ineffable Goodness, make them immutably blessed? If it be replied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he had already Created as many <hi>Species</hi> of immutable beings, as possibly he could, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was constrained to make them as they were, or else must not have made them at all. Then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand again, whether was this mutability essential to mans nature, or only a property and appendix inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with it? If it were essential, then how was CHRIST a perfect Man, his humane nature being ever void of that lapsibility, which is a constituent part, and prime ingredient of humanity? And what then will become of all men, that are at last translated to <hi>Caelestial</hi> happiness, and induced with a constant and inalterable nature? their essence must be quite abolished and destroyed, and they transmuted into other Creatures: If it be but a property or adjunct, why did not GOD separate it from them in their first Creation; since the abstraction and removal of it, would not have mutilated their essence (it being but a superfluous appendage of it) but have left the same every way absolute and entire? This I am sure would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54939:13"/> have been best for us, admitting we Praeexisted; and therefore the non-performance of it, to me is a plain demonstration, that GOD does not alwayes operate the <hi>best things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The result of the Premises is this; that though it had been <hi>best</hi> for the Souls of men, to have lived and acted in a divine state, <hi>Praecedaneous</hi> unto this upon Earth; yet GOD'S infinite Goodness is no conclusive Argument of the reality of the thing: Forasmuch as it is no Law of its nature, to do alwayes what is <hi>best;</hi> but rather to be subject to the motions of his <hi>Will,</hi> and to have its emanations regulated by that: So that unless that gave the <hi>fiat</hi> for <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> it could not be the product of infinite Goodness.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54939:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The second Argument for <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> borrowed from its eminent usefulness, insolving that harsh <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon</hi> of Providence, the <hi>exclusion of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, from the knowledge of the Gospel.</hi> 2. That difficulty explicable without the aid of <hi>Praeexistence.</hi> 3. For GOD is not the cause of that their misery, but <hi>themselves.</hi> 4. Either by <hi>rejecting</hi> the Gospel when offered to them. 5. Or by <hi>refusing</hi> to seek after it. 6. Or else by <hi>incapacitating</hi> themselves to receive it. 7. And the evill being thus resoluble into their own efficiency, ought not to laid upon GOD. 8. But if any be debarred from acquaintance with the Gospel, without their own default, tis probable they may be saved by the <hi>Light of Nature.</hi> 9. It being near a kin not only to the <hi>Mosaick-Law,</hi> but the <hi>Gospel</hi> it self. 10. And able with the assistance of the HOLY-GHOST, to carry men on to such Vertuous accomplishments, as will <hi>avail</hi> them to Eternal happiness. 11. Or if this cannot be effected without the intervention of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> they shall some way or other be <hi>Indoctrinated</hi> with it. 12. And that the <hi>Ethnicks</hi> in the state they are in, are capable of <hi>Felicity:</hi> The <hi>Sticklers</hi> for Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>existence must acknowledge; and this very agnition supersedes the necessity of their own <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> as to unfolding that Cloudy <hi>aenigme</hi> of Providence, the sad plight of the <hi>Heathen</hi> World.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. A Second Argument that the Patrons of <hi>Praeex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> furnish out in defence of their <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis;</hi> and next to be incountered, assaults us thus.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54939:14"/>
                  <hi>It is a necessary Key of divine Providence,</hi> without which those grand difficulties, that occur from the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of GOD'S rigid dealings with mankind, can never be fairly opened and unlocked; especially that epidemick blindness, brutishness and Paganism, that involves so many Nations, through the absence of the Gospel, will be a circumstance intricate and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable. It is too plain and manifest, that the case of most men is forlorn and lamentable; they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the Laws of CHRIST, and stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the means of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation.</hi> The cursed Empire of Hell, extends it self over the biggest part of the Earth, and the Inhabitants of it are perfect <hi>Vassals</hi> to the Devils Tyranny: <hi>Vice</hi> is enacted by their Laws, and <hi>Sin</hi> adopted into their Religion, and most nefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crimes received of them for solemn mysteries, and duties indispensable: And they are born under these unhallowed institutes, and trained up in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them, and setled in the belief and affection of them, by custom and education, <hi>Chronical</hi> practice and a number of associates; besides the pertinaceous and inexpugnable tendencies and proclivities of their corrupted nature to them; so that 'tis hardly possible they should escape them, but must inavoidably swim down the smooth, but perilous stream of <hi>licentiousness,</hi> till they be swallowed up in the Gulph of endless Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And is it conceivable that GOD who hath proclaimed himself to be <hi>Love</hi> unto men, and whose <hi>Mercies are over all his Works,</hi> should in his menages of the World, so far forget his declared <hi>Philanthropie,</hi> and the essential <hi>Compassionateness</hi> of his Nature, as to send down <hi>myriads</hi> of untainted Souls, the immediate off-spring of his powerfull Goodness (before they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54939:15"/> had any way offended) to dwell in Regions so misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly over-run with <hi>filthiness</hi> and <hi>barbarity;</hi> that in all probability they must be insnared and captivated by it, and for ever perish in a fatal compliance with it? No for certain, such an heavy calamity could never befall them here, but as the deserved punishment of some horrid guilt of theirs, and notoriously criminous deportment in a <hi>Pristine-state.</hi> But I Answer;</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the Intriques of Providence be dark <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> and mystical, and this in particular, deep and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; yet I doubt not but it may be cleverly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, without recourse to that <hi>garish</hi> Invention we have under debate: For grant the case of most men be sad and lamentable; that they are under the black Scepter of the Prince of Darkness; that their minds are inslaved to <hi>Atheism,</hi> or <hi>Polytheism, Superstition,</hi> or <hi>Prophaness;</hi> and that they have no intimacy with the Doctrine of <hi>Christianity,</hi> which should dis-intangle their <hi>illaqueated</hi> Consciences, and infranchise their Souls from the servitude of <hi>Vice:</hi> Yet we need not introduce <hi>Praeexistence</hi> to solve the misfortune, nor <hi>father</hi> this their infelicity on the miscarriages of a <hi>former</hi> state, to prevent daring reflections on <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> as if that were the <hi>Autrix</hi> of it; for in Truth it had no stroke at all in it, nor can it justly be intitled to an instrumentality in producing it, as I shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to evince.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That GOD had no hand, in stretching out that <hi>sable</hi> Cloud of ignorance, which obtenebrates so <hi>great</hi> a part of the World, is palpably plain from his own most infallible Word, in the 1 <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2. 4. where he expresly tells us, <hi>that he would have all men come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> which implies that he has
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54939:15"/> no mind to shut up any in Darkness and Error; but rather an unfeigned desire of their instruction, and scientifique illumination. Nor did he only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wish and desire this, but graciously attempt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of it too; for to this end he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Gospel unto men, a <hi>Pandect</hi> of the richest notions, the most celebrious and concerning truths imaginable; and by such hands as might render it most operative and influential: For that the <hi>Promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> credit, might conciliate to its authority, and make it more <hi>taking</hi> and <hi>impressive;</hi> he would have it first set on foot by no meaner one, than his own <hi>Blessed Son;</hi> and then carried on by the holy <hi>Ministery</hi> of Chosen and peculiar <hi>Predicants,</hi> his <hi>Apostles</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Emissaries;</hi> Persons eminent for their exemplary <hi>simpleness</hi> and <hi>integrity;</hi> dignified with the power of working Miracles, divinely instructed from above; and able by verte of their inspired Wisdom, to baffle and gull the learnedest of the Age, and to nonplus and confound the craftiest and nasutest <hi>Sophisters,</hi> that durst argue with them, from the Stock of humane reason, and acquired <hi>Literature.</hi> And that <hi>Caelestial</hi> Gospel, which was planted by these famous <hi>Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> still flourisheth in the World; and though they do not every where culminate to an equal <hi>procerity;</hi> yet there are few places into which that <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> hath not (at some time or other) dispread its <hi>verdant</hi> Branches, offering unto all its salutary Fruits, that will but take the pains to gather them: And if their be store of barren Wasts, and wild Deserts on the Earth, in which it never yet took Root and Fructified: These squalled Desolations must not be charged upon GOD'S <hi>Providence,</hi> as if that weighed out his Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54939:16"/> with inequal Ballances, giving all to some, and none to others; surfeting these <hi>Climes</hi> with satiety of knowledge, and famishing others for want of the same: But the real ground of the calamity, is to be sought for in the bosoms of men, and it will quickly appear to be of their <hi>own</hi> procuring: For wherever People are hood-winkt with a <hi>Pagan</hi> ignorance, and have the Word of <hi>Eternal</hi> truth concealed from them, I suppose they may thank <hi>themselves</hi> for it; it being for some of these reasons.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Either in the first place, because they unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>reject the tendries of it,</hi> refusing to admit it when it obtrudes it self upon their acceptance, and repelling it with churlish and <hi>Antichristian</hi> violence; when it importunes them for reception, when it offers to visit them as a Friend, they take it for an Enemy, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it with boisterous hostilities, and charging up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it furious oppositions, and so check its kind advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards them: They hugg their <hi>Chains,</hi> and love their <hi>Fetters;</hi> admire their <hi>Thraldom,</hi> and Court their <hi>Shackles;</hi> strangely doting on their infelicity, in that they are <hi>Captives</hi> unto Sin; and when the <hi>Gospel</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers its helping hand, to rescue and assert them into <hi>liberty,</hi> they scorn <hi>Redemption,</hi> and will <hi>still</hi> be drudges to their <hi>Lusts,</hi> not from necessity, but <hi>perverse</hi> Election. This is one principal cause of mens <hi>stupid</hi> ignorance of the <hi>Gospel;</hi> they will not beleive it, nor suffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be informed by it; the Sun of <hi>Truth</hi> in many places, shines gloriously on their dwellings, but they are <hi>shie</hi> of his <hi>Coruscant-beams,</hi> and shut their Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows against his <hi>light,</hi> choosing to spend their life in <hi>darkness,</hi> because it sutes best with their <hi>will-Works,</hi> which are alwayes shamefac't and lucifugous; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54939:16"/> this sayes the Great <hi>Evangelist,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that Light is come into the World, but Men love Darkness rather than Light, because their deeds are evill;</hi> So that 'tis not the want of Gospel <hi>Light,</hi> but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and disaffection of it that undoes the World: Men might be saved by it, even heathens themselves, did they not hate and shun it's influence and disdain to be subject to it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Or else a second reason why so many are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulphed in <hi>Atheisme</hi> and Idolatrie, while the glorious Gospel is latent and undiscovered to them may be, for that they incuriously <hi>neglect to seek it,</hi> and imploy their abilities in searching after it: The most inculti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Heathens</hi> we know are Men, and are endued with the natural perfections of <hi>Humanity;</hi> they have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and discourse, and understanding, and Judgment; by the help of which they can <hi>Dive</hi> into the nature of things, and easily distinguish <hi>truth</hi> from <hi>falshood,</hi> and discern the excellence of one Religion from another; so that if they would but rouz up themselves, and go in <hi>quest</hi> of the principles of <hi>Christianity,</hi> faithfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to retrive them, by their own industry, and the divine assistance (that would in so worthy a susception, edge their faculties with a keen <hi>sagacitie)</hi> they should undoubtedly attain the knowledge of them, and return with <hi>ingeminated orations</hi> in their mouths, every one vaunting the success of his <hi>scrutiny,</hi> with a joyous and Triumphant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But when GOD hath Graced mankind, with the publication of his Word unto some of them; and hath supplied the rest with requisite strengths, and means proper and <hi>idoneous</hi> to investigate it (else his affirming <hi>he would have all Men come to the knowledge of the Truth,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:54939:17"/> is a flat and downright mockery) and they sottishly recuse to prosecute the discovery of it, and to ingage their abilities in a sedulous inquisition after it; <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> must not be criminated, with their destitution of its knowledge. There are Scriptures in the World, containing a Religion of elevated principles, under the Conduct of which they might securely march to Heaven; but they are not so ambitious of its manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, as to seek the benefit of it; and while they so much vilipend and slight its guidance, no marvell if they lack it: For GOD expects they should stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diously contrive, and (so far as their powers will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) make way for their acquaintance with his Sacred Oracles; and if they think much to do this for it, they shall never gain it: He will not gratifie their Idleness so far, as to Crown their sluggish and torpid oscitancies, with what he hath made the reward of diligence.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Or Lastly, a third reason why <hi>whole</hi> Nations, and such multitudinous numbers of People, hear no ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Gospel, is because they have <hi>incapacitated themselves, for the reception of it:</hi> They are immersed so deep in sensuality, and grown so perfectly brutish and animal, and have so debauched their persons, by low degeneracies from rational and humane life; that they are become unmeet receptables of so divine a mercy, and have unquallified, and disabled themselves from reaping any profit by it: And GOD foreseeing this, that <hi>Evangelical</hi> monitions bestowed on them, would prove insuccessfull and frustraneous; wisely detains them, and forbears the imparture of his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to them, as <hi>Husbandmen</hi> do the proscision and culture of arenaceous Fields, of whose sterility they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54939:17"/> are well assured: And this I conceive was that, which occasioned the HOLY GHOSTS inhibition of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Preaching in <hi>Asia, Acts</hi> 16. and his avocation from <hi>Bithynia,</hi> whither he assayed to go to that end, but by a nocturnal Vision had his purpose interrupted, and his course diverted another way. GOD ('tis like) deemed the <hi>Asiatiques</hi> unworthy of his Word, and saw them incapable of receiving it, if it had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to them; and therefore permitted it not to be then taught amongst them, because the attempt he knew would be unprosperous: Nor need it seem a thing improbable, that men by nequitious practices should arrive at such a rude and savage temper, as to become indisciplinable by the Gospel, and upon that score to be secluded from it; for we must know, that by their subjection to the tyrannies of Lust, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary violences offered to them, the powers of their minds may be so shattered and dissolved, and the common notions of indispensable Truths written on their hearts, so obliterated and effaced: Reason, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Good and Evill, may be so debilitated and corrupted; and their whole nature moulded into such a strange incapacity, and contrariety to things Divine and excellent; that they shall by no means be wrought to embrace them, and close with them; but must remain as indocible by the Laws of GOD, as Brutes are by the Sanctions of men; and without a miraculous change of their blockish and ferine dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, will never be able to deprehend them, though most forcibly inculcated. Now where the Eye of Providence sees people at so untractable a pass; so wofully discomposed in their nature and faculties; so sadly besotted and brutified; and so perfectly Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54939:18"/> from true Goodness, as to be utterly senseless of the rules of honesty, and deaf to the precepts of Religion; no wonder if it denyes them the <hi>radiant</hi> Gospel, and lets them wander in <hi>Cimmerian</hi> darkness, because Light to them would be offensive and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome, and instruction vain and fruitless; and they would still live wildly and at random, in spite of the choicest Lectures of sobriety, that Heaven it self could read them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Into these three Ranks I conclude the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>generality</hi> of those <hi>Pagans</hi> reducible, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the Sacred Volumes, and ignorant of those Laws of Righteousness, and methods of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation therein exhibited. Either they are such as have <hi>oppugued</hi> the Gospel, and kept it off when it hath been fairly approaching towards them: Or else such as have supinely <hi>slighted</hi> it, and never Travelled accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their power, in a diligent search after it: Or Lastly, such as by living vitiously, and much beneath the dignity of their nature, have so unmeasurably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved themselves, as to become quite <hi>incapable</hi> of relishing its pure Doctrines, and obeying its holy dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and therefore were never instructed with it. And this much considerately weighed, though the greatest part of mankind; be muffled up with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and infidelitie, and possessed with an inscious and <hi>Atheistical</hi> spirit, and go on groping all their lives long in darkness and ignorance; yet their deplorable fate is at no hand to be imputed unto GOD, nor may his <hi>Providence</hi> be condemned as guilty of infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it: For it flows intirely from themselves, and that they have no knowledge of the Gospel, is owing to their own <hi>antipathy</hi> to it, disregard of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54939:18"/> it, or maliciously contracted ineptness for it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now if there be any in the World of a <hi>fourth Classis,</hi> distinct from these <hi>three</hi> here remember'd, who have kept their intellectuals sound and perfect, and their affections clear from all grosser inquinations: Whose reason is not so absorpt and drowned in the puddles of sense, nor nummed and deaded by the <hi>narcotick</hi> pleasures of the Body, and a constant and vehement love and attendance to carnal delights, as to render them unfit to receive the Gospel: And who never unkindly repulsed, or scornfully despised it, and so put in an <hi>Obex</hi> to hinder its accession to them; but so far as a plausible and civill Life could do it, have pursued it, and prepared themselves for it. If there be any such in the World I say, from whom the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is with-held, and not through their own defaults, they doing what they can to invite and lure it to them, by praedisposing themselves, so far as they are able to comply with it, and entertain it. Yet neither will this infer a necessity of <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> to acquit <hi>Providence</hi> from injurious dealings with them; for though their condition be hugely pitiable, it is far from desperate; and if they live but up to that <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> which is within them, and those <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or commune instincts of Good and Evill (imprinted on their Souls, at their first Creation) we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume that GOD hath a great mercy for them, and may save them through the <hi>All-sufficient</hi> merits of his Crucified Son, by wayes and methods known to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, though unrevealed to us.</p>
               <p>And here if I thought the Truth of this Doctrine, that <hi>Heathens</hi> may be saved by the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> would be scrupled; I might call forth a number of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54939:19"/>
                  <hi>able</hi> Advocates to plead for it; and confirm it by a copious induction of undeniable testimonies, out of choice and noted Writers, both <hi>Antique</hi> and <hi>Neoterick;</hi> and to make it pass the more currently, it will not be amiss to stamp it with some of their Autorities: <hi>Dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Disciple, and the first Bishop of <hi>Athens,</hi> held that all virtuous livers (though without the pale of Holy Church) might gain felicity, GOD illuminating them with a knowledge requisite thereunto, by the Ministry of Men or Angels. <hi>De Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest. Hier. cap.</hi> 9. St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> taught, that before the Incarnation the true acknowledgment of CHRIST was not exacted, but that the adoration of the true GOD would carry men to Heaven. <hi>Hom. 3. in Mat.</hi> St. <hi>Augustine</hi> thought that some living under the Law of Nature, obtained Salvation. <hi>Cont. Jul. lib. 4. cap. 3. Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> avers, that GOD gave <hi>two</hi> Testaments; the Law to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Philosophy to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whereby to Justifie them. <hi>Strom. lib. 6. Justin Martyr</hi> affirms, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> who lived <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, agreeably to their Reason, were real <hi>Christians;</hi> and such he esteemed <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> and other <hi>Heathens</hi> to be. <hi>Melancton</hi> thought very charitably of the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and more refined <hi>Ethnicks;</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> had hopes of <hi>Brentius</hi> and <hi>Cicero. Zuinglius</hi> speaks broad in the case, and sayes plainly that in Heaven he shall behold <hi>Hercules, Theseus, Socrates, Numa,</hi> with other Ancient Virtuosoes: And of the same mind was his Apologist <hi>Gualtherus.</hi> To these I might add the Suffrages of <hi>Epiphanius, Ludovicus Vives, Venator, Corvinus, Collius, Andradius,</hi> and many others (were it not superfluous to recite them) all which unanimously vote Salvation possible to the <hi>Heathen,</hi> by the Light of Nature; that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54939:19"/> is, in conjunction with the efficacious sufferings, and perfect obedience of CHRIST, though some would perversly insinuate that they mean otherwise: The last here nominated stifly maintained the Paradox, in the <hi>Tridentine Council,</hi> and is most severely lashed for his pains by <hi>Chemnitius,</hi> in his <hi>Examen</hi> of the Decrees of its sixth <hi>Session;</hi> yet neither did that <hi>Council</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing against the point (though he put an occasion offered by the said <hi>Andradius,</hi> and others also of the same <hi>Senate,</hi> efflagitated their Censure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision of it) but left it free and indifferent, as a <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis</hi> of very high probability, if not unquestionable certitude.</p>
               <p>And to prove the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> a sufficient guide to Blessedness (in the absence of a surer conduct) I might argue thus; that the <hi>Mosaick Law</hi> inducted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls to happiness, is a truth of undoubted credit, (for this was the great and ultimate scope at which its whole subserviency was levelled) and what was that but the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> published, and drawn up into a methodicall system of holy Mandates, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine instructions? And if the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moses,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> be the same; if GOD saved the <hi>Jews,</hi> under the Administration of the first, what hinders but he may save the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> under the Paedagogie of the later?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Now that these <hi>two</hi> Laws, are <hi>substantially</hi> the same, may be made good by most evictive evidence; for wherein do they differ, save that the <hi>Moral</hi> Law was openly promulged to a peculiar People, orderly digested into several Precepts, and distinctly Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>Stony</hi> Tables; whereas the other was only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in the minds of Men? And as for that other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54939:20"/> discrepance between them, that the <hi>Moral</hi> Law had many appendages fastened on it, which the <hi>Natural</hi> had not; various Rites and Ceremonies joyned to it, that were <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Symbols, Ʋmbrages</hi> and <hi>Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> of future things, this did not at all hinder their <hi>Identity;</hi> for these were meerly <hi>Thetical</hi> and <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial,</hi> not at all essential to, or constitutive of, that <hi>immutuable</hi> Law whereunto they are annexed, which appears manifestly, in that the Law still remains intire, though these extrinsique and appendent Ordinances, be long since nulled and prescinded, by an eternal sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
               <p>Besides, that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> are one and the same, as to the chief strokes and contents of them, is colligible from <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14. where the <hi>Apostle</hi> sayes expresly that <hi>Nations without the Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, can do by Nature the things contained in the Law;</hi> but how could they, unless the prime duties of both were the same, and consequently the Laws themselves, as to the <hi>substance</hi> of them cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondent and identical? And the very next verse tells us, that they have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Work of the Law Written in their Hearts,</hi> which keeps their Consciences in so wakefull and rouzed a posture, that they are able upon all occasions, to <hi>accuse,</hi> or <hi>excuse</hi> them in their doings, according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their Actions, as the same Text assures us; and if we look back to the <hi>first Chapter</hi> of the same <hi>Epistle,</hi> and consult the <hi>nineteenth, twentieth,</hi> and one and <hi>twentieth verses</hi> of it, we shall find that the most important duties of the <hi>Mosaick Law</hi> (as the <hi>knowing GOD, the understanding of his Eternal Power and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the Glorifying, and Praising, and Worshipping, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54939:20"/> Serving his Adorable Majesty)</hi> may be executed, and in a good measure fulfilled by the light and energy of reason and Conscience; and this still evinceth a great congruency of the <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Mosaick</hi> Law, and mutual <hi>sameness</hi> of both, in their most weighty and essential Requisites.</p>
               <p>And farther the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> having so near an Affinity with the <hi>Jewish,</hi> it must needs claim a propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and alliance to the <hi>Christian</hi> Law also, as indeed it does: For it is the Root and Basis of that dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Grand Argument, upon which the <hi>New-Testament</hi> is in great part, a <hi>lucid</hi> Paraphrase: It is a compendious <hi>Epitome</hi> of those momentous Doctrines, more copiously taught by the Holy JESUS, and the <hi>Gospel</hi> it self, in its first and imperfect Edition; so that being thus nearly related, both to the <hi>Moral</hi> Law, and <hi>Evangelical,</hi> it would be more absurd, that <hi>Heathens</hi> by a vigilant observance of it, should not be saved, than that they should.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Now if it be here objected, that the Reason of most <hi>Pagans</hi> is exceeding flat and low, and that their endeavours after virtue, must therefore be so tepid, that they will hardly ever be Crowned with such perfection in it, as is requisite to make them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipants of future happiness. It will be Answered, let them do but what they can, and they shall be assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in the acquisition of such Moral excellencies, as will be rewardable with Eternal <hi>Benedictions:</hi> For if they strive but sincerely to extricate themselves, from the intanglements of Sin, and set their faces towards Heaven, in the resolute aggressions of Justice and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty, they shall quickly feel their debility corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and their imbecilled powers fortified by divine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54939:21"/>
                  <hi>Auxilia,</hi> aids and subsidies from above; for I doubt not but if the HOLY GHOST, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and intimately acquainted with all mens dispositions, once sees these poor Creatures verging towards the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests of Piety, though never so little; he will imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately strike in with them, confirm them in their choice, help forwad their intentions, direct them in their progress, and supply the place of <hi>Evangelical</hi> Precepts, Councils and admonitions to them; till they arise to such degrees of Purity, as may qualifie them in GOD'S account to Life and Salvation: For we must not think that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of GOD, goes no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his <hi>Word,</hi> and that where the <hi>Bible</hi> is not Read, its <hi>Operations</hi> are not felt. No, that as it finds occasion takes a larger Circuit; visits the darkest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of the World; and many times sallies forth in powerfull influences on the Inhabitants thereof; as well as on them that live within the precincts of the Church, and sit under the gleams of <hi>Gospel</hi> Light. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Spirit bloweth where it listeth;</hi> and if it meets with the least spark of genuine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, though raked up in never so many Ashes of <hi>Pagan</hi> corruptions, it will do what in reason can be desired, to ventilate and Fan it into a burning flame: What the Author of the Book of <hi>Wisdom (Philo</hi> as some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive) excellently delivers of the HOLY GHOST, does most appositely quadrate with him; namely, <hi>That he is ready to do Good, kind to Man, and in all ages entring into Holy Souls, maketh them Friends of GOD.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wisd 7. 22. 23. 27.</note> He is not bound to <hi>time</hi> or <hi>place,</hi> or any such like Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance; but with a free and unconfined liberty, rangeth through all <hi>times</hi> and <hi>Countreys,</hi> and where he lights on any that are susceptible of them, he Seals
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54939:21"/> them with divine impresses, and by his mighty Blessing secundates their pursuits of Virtue in this present life, and consigns them to the fruition of a better: So that grant the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which blinketh in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Heathens,</hi> be <hi>dim</hi> and <hi>luridous;</hi> and that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertions of their <hi>innate</hi> Reason, be faint and flaccid; yet being actuated by the HOLY GHOST, and cherisht with his potent and benign Workings, they may thus wax bright and vigorous, and be able to exalt them to such a pitch of Goodness, as will carry them to Immortality.</p>
               <p>Thus is <hi>Providence</hi> abundantly justified in her dealings with the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and fairly vindicated from all calumniative <hi>obloquies,</hi> and just suspicions of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and crudelity to their Souls, for placing them in so sad a constitution of things: For though they be surrounded with multifarious difficulties, and every where begirt with huge incumbrances; yet GOD hath fixed such principles in them, that if they be true and faithfull to them, by the <hi>adjument</hi> of the SPIRIT, they may emerge victoriously through them all, and maugre the strongest impediments in their way, ascend to <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Beatitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. But if it be too venturous and temerarious a dogmatizing, to vouch the Salvation of <hi>Heathens</hi> pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, without an <hi>explicit</hi> Knowledge of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> and the Holy <hi>Gospel</hi> (as I am forward to yield it is, if it shall be so sensed by the judicious) then we may wave that, as a loud conjecture, and without offence conclude them capable of felicity, upon another <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothosis;</hi> that is, the morigerous of them, and such as are truly obsequious to the commands of their inward Reason; for if their impotence be so great, that they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54939:22"/> cannot though aided by the ordinary concurrence of the HOLY GHOST (whose officious Goodness is ready to countenance the most frigid offers at Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and promote the sickliest endeavours after it) acquire such eminent portions of integrity, as may hallow their persons (through the meritorious Cross of JESUS) to an admission into Heaven: Then we may lawfully beleive, that they shall be tenderly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded of the Saviour of the World; and if they keep their pullulating Vertues, in a florid and thriving con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, shall themselves at length be transplanted into a nobler Soil, where those hopefull <hi>germinations,</hi> that begin to bud and sprout within them, being seasonably irrigated with the <hi>faecundant</hi> showers, and kindly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered with the <hi>benign</hi> influence of the Gospel, shall thereby ripen into high perfections, and the Graces of <hi>Christianity.</hi> Then GOD whose Providence su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintends the World, and whose mercy hovers over the whole Creation, gently brooding it with indulgent Wings; <hi>who is Good, and does Good, and ever waiteth to be Gracious;</hi> will lovingly watch over their teeming Souls, and not suffer the injected seeds of Goodness, to starve in the Womb of their conception, for lack of knowledge to feed and nourish them; but by means usual or extraordinary, will reduce them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the sound of his Word, and afford them so full an insight and erudition in <hi>Evangelical</hi> Mysteries, as shall minister effectually to their progress in Religion, and advance them to such measures of <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,</hi> as shall avail to their Eternal glorification, and together with the Key of CHRIST'S precious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, open unto them the Gates of <hi>Paradise.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. And this much the <hi>Assertors</hi> of <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54939:22"/> from their own principles bound to concede, that the <hi>Heathen</hi> in the condition they are in, are capable of Salvation: For they perswade that GOD'S sending them down into this <hi>Terrestrial</hi> Life, is an instance of his singular kindness to them (to use their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage;) <hi>an after Game of divine Goodness; and a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lux <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>mercy:</hi> But wherein lies this Goodness, or consists this mercy, unless it be in that they are here made <hi>Candidates,</hi> and <hi>Probationers</hi> for their lost Felicity, and put in a possibility of regaining it? And if it be possible for them in the case they are in, to attain hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness in the Life to come; we need no other <hi>Key</hi> to unlock the Methods of <hi>Providence</hi> to them, than this Doctrine; for it clears it from all accessotines to their ruine, and if they miscarry in the future State, it transfers their destruction upon themselves, and brands them for the procurers of their own mischief. And thus the high pretended usefulness, of the <hi>Origenian</hi> Hypothesis, to explicate the recondit mysteries of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Heathens</hi> Misery, is by its own <hi>Abettors</hi> most unluckily over-turned, and the Opinion rendered quite superfluous, as to that great work, for the transaction of which they hold it so very necessary: For if they once grant that the <hi>Heathen</hi> are in a capacity of aspiring to <hi>Caelestial</hi> Bliss (which they cannot deny, supposing this Life a mercy to them) then without any farther ado, the misery of <hi>Pagans</hi> in their want of the Gospel, and the equity of <hi>Providence</hi> in suffering this their misery, will from hence be made consistent, and reconcileable enough; though <hi>Praeex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence</hi> had never been excogitated, or were eternally exploded. The <hi>Circumstances</hi> they are in, are extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sad, but so long as GOD has not praecluded to them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54939:23"/> the way to Heaven, his bounty towards them is Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious, and we need not fetch in <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> to justifie his dealings with them. If he be accused as guilty of injuring them, we have evidence enough to prove him innocent, without suborning so false a Witness; I mean in that Court, where unfeigned <hi>Piety</hi> sits as Judge, and solid reason is of the <hi>Jury.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. A Third Argument for <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> fetcht from its trim <hi>solution</hi> of that knotty <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Problem;</hi> the <hi>Dispersion</hi> of <hi>Original</hi> Sin through the whole Stock of <hi>Mankind.</hi> 2. That this is sufficiently intelligible without that <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis.</hi> 3. A succinct description of <hi>Adams</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radisiacal happiness. 4. And the evill conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of his <hi>Apostasie.</hi> 5. The seat and vehicle of <hi>Original</hi> Sin to his Posterity, may be only the <hi>depraved Bodies,</hi> they draw from him since his defection. 6. That this Supposal granted, the manner of its <hi>Universal diffusion</hi> is very concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable. 7. That the uniting of Souls to these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminant Bodies, does not intrench at all upon GOD'S <hi>Justice.</hi> 8. An <hi>objection</hi> touching our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54939:23"/> notion of Original Sin, Answered. 9. A brief recapitulation of the <hi>Principals</hi> of the Chapter.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THE former Argument respected mans misery, this next relateth to his Sin; but is of a far larger extent and more comprehensive Latitude. For whereas the other pointed only at the <hi>Heathen;</hi> this referreth to the World collectively. And thus it runs;</p>
               <p>That <hi>Praeexistence</hi> is the only expedient, to unrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> the traduction of <hi>Original</hi> Sin, or rather the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune and epidemick contagion thereof: For thus, every one will be made the Author of his own <hi>primor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial</hi> Guilt; and we need not have recourse to GOD'S Transactions with the person of <hi>Adam,</hi> and so run into a maze or <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of difficulties, out of which their is no extrication: Then we need not puzzle and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex our selves, about the secret and imperscrutable mode of its devolution upon us; nor make any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous reflections on the Attribute of GOD'S <hi>Justice,</hi> for plunging <hi>immaculate</hi> Spirits into defiling Bodies; who did not in the least concur with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in his foul offence, nor any way consent to the perpetration of it, they not so much as potentially existing in him, at the time of his revolt. I Reply;</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this is one way to expound that <hi>Mystick</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> Head in Divinity, it will freely be acknowledged: But to pronounce it the sole means of its <hi>enodation,</hi> is too elated and <hi>Thrasonick</hi> a glorying in the <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> and savours as much of <hi>Falshood,</hi> as <hi>Arrogance:</hi> For I doubt not but a very full, and plausible account of that arduous point, neither too difficil to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, nor diminutive of GOD'S most perfect <hi>Justice,</hi> is as inferrible from other principles, as from this; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54939:24"/> to propose such a solution of that abstruse mystery, the propagation of <hi>Original</hi> guilt, as is free from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected criminations, of too great <hi>difficulty</hi> and <hi>dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> from the Divine <hi>Equity,</hi> shall be my next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that we may tread on the surer grounds in doing it, it will not be amiss to fetch a little the larger circuit, and cursorily to traverse the Felicity of <hi>Adam,</hi> in his state of innocence.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>High</hi> JEHOVAH then, being infinitely perfect, and so <hi>perfectly</hi> Blessed in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; though he could not thereby gain any <hi>new</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, to his own <hi>intrinsique</hi> happiness; yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate his Wisdom and Power, and to make himself receptacles of his <hi>boundless Goodness,</hi> which is ever prone to Benefactions; <hi>He</hi> resolved to Create several sorts of <hi>Beings,</hi> and to bless them with the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of his <hi>Paternal</hi> Bounty, according to their respective capacities. Hereupon he first of all produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, an <hi>immense</hi> moles of corporeal substance; which in the beginning, was one dark and confused <hi>Chaos;</hi> but being reduced into that <hi>Elegant</hi> and <hi>Concumous</hi> order in which now it stands, it became that goodly Fabrick call'd the <hi>World;</hi> which was no sooner reared, but the skilfull <hi>Architect</hi> that fram'd it, took care to furnish and adorn it with <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> and to <hi>sute</hi> their Natures to the <hi>qualities</hi> of their provided Mansions. Thus because the <hi>Heavens,</hi> or <hi>supernal</hi> Regions, are fraught with nothing but GOD'S own presence, and a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>Tenuious</hi> substance; he stored them with <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Intelectual</hi> Powers, the <hi>Fines</hi> of whose Essence perhaps, abhors all <hi>vital</hi> Union with the purest matter. The <hi>Lower</hi> World, I mean the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54939:24"/>
                  <hi>Erratick</hi> Globe we live on, as being a lump of course and drossie <hi>Corporeity,</hi> he stockt with various <hi>Animals,</hi> whose crass and ruder constitutions, <hi>symbolized</hi> with the <hi>Elements</hi> of their appointed Residence. Thus, <hi>Fish</hi> were fitted for the Waters: <hi>Fowls</hi> and <hi>Beasts,</hi> &amp;c. for the upper <hi>Cortex</hi> of the Earth, and <hi>ambient</hi> Air: Nor were the <hi>Interior</hi> Regions of our <hi>Planet,</hi> left a naked Desolation, but perhaps were peopled with their proper <hi>Incolae,</hi> and had their close <hi>Recesses,</hi> silent <hi>Vaults</hi> and hollow <hi>Caverns,</hi> garnisht with such <hi>Beings,</hi> as love those Nightsom <hi>Cells,</hi> and subterraneous <hi>Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This done, he took in hand the <hi>efformation</hi> of Man, a Curious and most Noble piece of <hi>Workmanship.</hi> For him, he made the <hi>lively</hi> Transcript of himself, <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterizing</hi> his Person with the <hi>Image</hi> of his Deity: Which though it consisted mainly, in the <hi>rectitude</hi> and <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> of his mind, yet some obscurer <hi>Lineaments</hi> of it, were conspicuous in the <hi>immaterial</hi> and <hi>Immortal</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his Soul; his rational and lofty faculties, and Dominion over his <hi>Fellow</hi> Creatures. For that he might bear the more exact <hi>similitude,</hi> and just <hi>resemblance</hi> of himself, GOD set him on a splendent <hi>Throne,</hi> and rais'd him to a kind of <hi>Royal Supremacy,</hi> over all the <hi>Bestial</hi> Communities: Who, so long as he held his <hi>Primative</hi> Station, were Faithfull in their due <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> to him, and greatly delighted to admire, and serve their deputed <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Emperour:</hi> Nor indeed could they <hi>Shift</hi> it; for such a placid refulgency sat upon his Countenance, and such <hi>sparkling</hi> and <hi>perstrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> beams of Majesty fallied from his Eyes, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Look</hi> he cast upon them, darted wonder into their Souls; awed them down to reverential prostrations,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54939:25"/> and extorted from them, <hi>tacit</hi> significations of their subjection to him: Nor had he more command, or less obedience <hi>without,</hi> than he had <hi>within</hi> himself: For then his Body was wholly swayed by the <hi>Empire</hi> of his mind, and naturally conspired with its regular and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring motions: His <hi>Nerves</hi> abounded with <hi>Agil</hi> Spirits, and his turgid <hi>Veins</hi> with well concocted Blood: His <hi>Heat</hi> was soft and gentle; and his <hi>Ferments</hi> smooth and unctuous; and all his <hi>Members</hi> vegete and lively; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prest for the service of his Will, and free to execute the <hi>Mandates</hi> of it, without the least check, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranitency to the same.</p>
               <p>And that his <hi>Habitation,</hi> might correspond to the dignity of his Person, he was seated in <hi>Paradise,</hi> a Promptuary of rich Felicities; a place confert and crowded full with innocent oblectations, and beset on all sides with such high contentments, that nothing but Heaven could be like it. Where besides the luscious gratifications, of his chast and wary senses, which he plentifully imbibed; he swam in <hi>Torrents</hi> of Diviner Joyes, that frankely flowed from the indulgence of his <hi>Maker:</hi> For ever and anon he was taken up into familiar converse with him, and saw his Glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence under some <hi>visible Form</hi> or other; the frequent sight and vived sense of which, threw him into such gratefull <hi>Extasies,</hi> and so transported his enravisht Soul, with <hi>Sentiments</hi> of <hi>Angelick</hi> pleasure, vigorous emotions of mind, and strong <hi>Aspires</hi> of <hi>Seraphick</hi> Love, as almost to heave her out of her new espoused Body. And though he was not alwayes actuated with these <hi>pathetick</hi> Raptures, yet he had wherewith to stave off <hi>dumpish</hi> Stupors, and to keep himself in a Triumphant posture; for when the <hi>Paroxisms</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54939:25"/> were over, and the <hi>Tide</hi> of Consolations at an Ebb; yet the memory of them so lately past, and the lively hopes of their speedy returne, could not but cause the <hi>lesser</hi> Springs of Joy, to rise and bubble in his Soul, and to continue gurgling through his heart, till fresh approaches of the <hi>Shechinah</hi> pull'd up the Sluce again, and delug'd him with <hi>new,</hi> and happy inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thus transcendently Blessed was the <hi>Protoplast,</hi> when he first dropt out of his Creators hands: But he stood not long in this condition; the <hi>Scaene</hi> was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed, and the Garland of Felicity that adorn'd his <hi>temples,</hi> instead of proving immarcescible, withered in a moment: How it came to do so I must next relate, together with the evill and deplorable circumstances, of his great Misfortune.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What a rare and incomparable state of <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>first</hi> man was honoured with, I have briefly hinted; and if he had but persisted in a due conformity to the Will of GOD, and cautelously shunned all <hi>sinister</hi> declensions from his Righteous <hi>Laws;</hi> he should thereby have ensured to himself, and entailed on his Posterity, a continuation of those high prerogatives, which he injoyed: And how really desirous GOD was of this, that <hi>Adam</hi> should have held his <hi>first</hi> sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and so have conveyed down the Priviledges of it, to succedent Generations; is plain, in that he did not only indue him with sufficient strengths, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his incumbent duties; but to make him vigilant in acting of them; severely threatned, that if he failed in his obedience, he should <hi>surely Dye, Gen.</hi> 2. 17. But he indiscreetly slighting the denounced <hi>menaces,</hi> rashly complyed with the <hi>Serpents</hi> suggestions, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the express interdiction of ALMIGHTY
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54939:26"/> GOD, praevaricated his <hi>Holy</hi> Sanctions, inadvisedly rushing on the instances of disloyalty: But his delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencies cost him dear; for thereby he incurred the forfeiture of all his happiness, and being made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the <hi>minatory</hi> Sentence, died in most of his capacities. And that he did not dye <hi>Eternally,</hi> is to be Attributed to Heavens pity, which interposed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and Hell, and snatcht the unworthy sinner from so dire a misery: But that which must be noted, as most pertinent to our purpose is, that his <hi>Fall</hi> was very destructive to his <hi>Body;</hi> that it changed the Temperature, corrupted the Habit, and mightily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the constitution of it: So that whereas, before it was of a flexible and yeilding nature, and sequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the dictates of his unspotted mind; cool and calm, and entirely subject unto reasons conduct; he had no sooner transgrest the <hi>lines</hi> of Innocence, by unluckie combination with the Devil, but he found himself in another World: For presently unbridled passion, usurpt the Throne of his deposed Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, cast off its Empire, and disseiz'd it of its just Dominion; turbulent affections tyranniz'd over his impotent Spirit; and brutish desires, impatient of Controll, hurried him on to unlawfull objects, with most praecipitant and fierce <hi>impetuosity;</hi> his <hi>proclivities</hi> to Vice were made well nigh insuperable; and his <hi>Antipathies</hi> to Virtue so strong and deadly, that he could never buckle to the practice of it, but by assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous conflicts with his reluctant flesh, and frequent repetitions of most sharp <hi>Psycomachies:</hi> In a word, when he sinned, he came under the power of a raging Principle, whose fury as yet he never felt: Then <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulant</hi> Sense, which before kept under <hi>Hatches,</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54939:26"/> lay bound in Fetters of a due restraint, brake loose and perkt aloft; and clambering into the <hi>Acropolis</hi> of his Soul, could make a shift to fool and baffle his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler faculties, and to tempt him on to sad <hi>altaxies</hi> and <hi>miscarriages:</hi> So that whereas before he might vie <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> with the Angels, as being their <hi>Younger</hi> Brother, and near allied to their exalted Race and <hi>Hierarchie;</hi> by infringing Heavens Statutes, he degenerated from his high perfections, and through his own praeposte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous folly, became a Companion of the Beasts that perish; was linked to a sensual noisom Carcass, and made a Stage for <hi>Wanton</hi> appetites, and base carnality to act upon, as well as they.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And thus perhaps we have discovered what is that true <hi>Vehiculum,</hi> and general Channel, which so faithfully derives the impure stream of <hi>Original guilt,</hi> to every Child of rebellious <hi>Adam;</hi> namely distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, unweildy, and praedominant Bodies, which he propagated to them; for he having by his cursed <hi>Anomies,</hi> depraved his own <hi>Crasts,</hi> and being unable to transmit purer Bodies to his <hi>Issue,</hi> than he had him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; they receiving from him gross and faeculent ones, from their very first unition to them, were inevitably tinctured with naughty propensions, and a vile Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupisence; and that the Body infects the Soul with <hi>Original Sin,</hi> the CHURCH of <hi>England</hi> plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares; for she calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which according <note place="margin">Articl<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 9.</note> to those reditions of the Word, that she sets down; signifies the <hi>sensuality, affection, and desire of the Flesh;</hi> and clearly intimates, that she looks upon those ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement lustings, and filthy inclinations, that consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>Original Sin,</hi> as accruing to us from our concrete <hi>Flesh,</hi> which sinks and weighs us down, and irresistibly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54939:27"/> hurries us away into those obliquities: And that these <hi>putid</hi> Dungeons which we dwell in, should thus strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly influence our Souls, as to infect them with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore said guilt, is not strange at all; for if we consult our own experience, and mark how exactly our minds conform and answer to our Bodies, and change and vary with the same; and how much the distemper of the one, indisposeth the other, affecting it with <hi>dulness, frowardness, phrenzie,</hi> &amp;c. according to the nature of the <hi>regnant</hi> malignity; we cannot but confess, that the result of our Souls so <hi>intimate</hi> Union with these <hi>Trunks</hi> of Flesh, disordered grievously by the <hi>first</hi> Mans intemperance; may very well be an <hi>excessive</hi> Love to sensibles, and rank disgust of inward <hi>Purity,</hi> which two <hi>Evils</hi> integrate the Nature of <hi>Original Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. And allowing this, to be a genuine <hi>Notion</hi> of it, which I have proposed; <hi>viz.</hi> That it is a discomposure of the Soul; a debilitation and deordination of her faculties, proceeding from that rude <hi>inert,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governable Body, to which she is <hi>vitally</hi> United; it may easily be deprehended, how the <hi>Guilt</hi> of it should become so <hi>Catholique</hi> as it is; and so generally descendent upon every Man: For <hi>Adam</hi> by his <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication,</hi> having brought down the Curse of Heaven upon his Head, it wrought a <hi>dismal</hi> mutation in his Body, which made it stout and refractory, stubborn and Rebellious; and apt not only to hinder the <hi>Spirit</hi> in its motion upward, and retard it in doing what GOD requires; but also to press it down-ward with a <hi>mighty</hi> degravation, and to stimulate and spur it on, to <hi>Lawless</hi> disconformities, to the <hi>Heavenly</hi> Will: And he being the <hi>commune</hi> source, and Parent of Mankind, from whom our Bodies by way of <hi>Generation,</hi> were
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54939:27"/> all derived; they must needs be of the same <hi>enormous</hi> temper with his own; and consequently productive of the like sinfull exorbitancies in our Souls, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon their <hi>Syzygie,</hi> or conjunction; so that hence it is apparent enough, how our Nature came to be <hi>poisoned</hi> with such head-strong proclivities, to sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual turpitude, and to affect such wide <hi>eccentricities</hi> to real Goodness; or which is all one, how we came to be besmeard with <hi>Original Sin:</hi> It was not done by any cryptick transmission, or unintelligible disse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of it from <hi>Adam's</hi> Soul, as some would have it; for then his <hi>Virtues,</hi> might as well have been trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused into us, as his <hi>Sin;</hi> a good habit being as apt to migrate from the <hi>Father</hi> to the <hi>Children,</hi> as an evill one: Nor by any <hi>fatal Decrce</hi> transferring it upon us, by imputation; for <hi>Original Sin</hi> is not only an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, but a Physical and inherent thing, radicated and grounded in us; <hi>a Fault, Corruption, and infection</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Artic. 9.</note>
                  <hi>of our Nature,</hi> as our <hi>Church</hi> hath solidly defined it: But it springs from the Souls copulation, with this lumpish <hi>foetid</hi> Body; which clogs her with a drowzy indisposition to Goodness, and alienating her mind, from the proper objects of her <hi>masculine</hi> faculties, draws her down into a slavish affectation of, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous egression after animal delights, which we name Concupiscence.</p>
               <p>Nor need we wonder (as I said before) that our noisom Bodies, should so far over-power the indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Souls, as to determine them into sinfull motions, and to stain them with such an early guilt: For such a potent agency have these muddy Prisons, on the Spirits immured in them; and with so strange a sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy, do they bewitch and charm them into compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54939:28"/> with fordid and ignoble interests; that I am ready to believe; if Blessed <hi>Angels,</hi> Creatures of an higher order than our selves (though some deny it) were incarcerated in them after the same manner that we are; they would be as deeply conscious of those innate pravities called <hi>Original Sin,</hi> as any of us all: I, and perhaps of actual impieties too, supposing they could forget their past felicities, and have their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of the other life, contracted into the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowness of ours: For then were they to act in these eadaverous Bodies; I doubt not but external objects, and the dolose baits of Sin, would be as cogent ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives of their passions, as now they are of ours; and playing briskly upon their Spirits, through the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their fleshly Organs, would Lord it over their intelligent part; and hazard with an high and domineering hand, to carry them Captive in the Chains of sense, unless they were extreamly vigilant. But this is an excursion; I therefore stop it, and return.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Now if it be here demanded, how it comports with the Justice of the GOD-HEAD, to immerse pure and upright Creatures, into such brutish and polluting vehicles, where they must necessarily be touched with Concupiscence, and tied up to constant bickerings and colluctations with raging lusts, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent passions? To the <hi>Quaery</hi> I shape out this Answer. Supposing GOD had created all men at once, and they had all existed at the same time with <hi>Adam;</hi> if then they had voluntarily lapsed together, and of their own accord, had slid down into the evill cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, and annoyances of their present state; GOD'S Justice should then have been acquitted by all, and every mouth would have proclaimed him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54939:28"/> of their misery; nor is he more guilty of it now: For he clearly foresaw, that if he had brought them all into Being at once, and set them down in the same happy condition with <hi>Adam;</hi> they would all have fallen from it, as he did (and his evill Fate may serve as one good Argument to convince us of as much) and foreseeing this, he did not make them <hi>coaetaneous</hi> with <hi>Adam</hi> (for all the Generations of Men, could not have subsisted on the Earth at once) but chose rather to create their Souls by <hi>piece-meal,</hi> and to let them derive their Bodies from him; that so they might live here successively one after another, in the same condition, into which they would infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have thrown themselves, if they had been <hi>Adams</hi> Contemporaries; so that the connexion of spotless Souls, with these foul and polluent Bodies, is no whit repugnant to divine <hi>Justice;</hi> for GOD herein did but inflict that calamity upon them, which if he had created them in a better state, and given them liberty of Election, would assuredly have been the Fruit of their <hi>own choice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that instead of reputing it an injury, we have reason to sense it as a special kindness of GOD, that he was pleased to take an occasion from <hi>Adams</hi> diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to Cloath us primarily with these collapsed, and ruinous Bodies: For if we had inchoated our lives in vehicles of a finer composition, and afterwards had vitiated, and dispoiled them by Sin, like our first Progenitor, as most certainly we should; this would have exposed us to great inconveniencies, which are now prevented: For then in the <hi>First</hi> place, our Mansion in embased and discomposed Bodies, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once joyned unto better; would have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54939:29"/> more troublesome and uneasy, than now it is: As it is most grievous to such as have resided in stately Palaces, to be confined to nasty Cottages: And most intolerable to delicate livers, to come under the pressures, and pungent asperities of angust fortunes, and adverse contingencies. And again it would have aggravated, and ingrandized our <hi>Original Sin,</hi> and rendered it obnoxious to the severest penances; whereas by this means it is extenuated, and made less punishable and flagitious; for we receiving the guilt of it at second hand, by derivation from our <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative,</hi> it must needs be less hainous, than if it had been contracted by personal curvities, and malicious declensions from the Rules of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> into which we should undoubtedly have swerved: And since we have both less Sin, and less Punishment, by our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugation with these vile <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, than would have redounded to us, if we had been united to Bodies more defaecate; GOD is not so <hi>unjust,</hi> as <hi>meroiful</hi> in the Dispensation.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I should here have put an end to this Chapter, but that a pert objection tuggs me by the sleeve, and will not be pacified without an Answer. It expresseth it self in these terms: If what I presume of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> be true concerning it; namely that it results im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, from the <hi>conjunction of the Soul with a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Body;</hi> then how could CHRIST evade the pollution of it, and stand (as it is certain he did) in a compleat immunity from it?</p>
               <p>To this I reply first, that his Body ('tis like) was of a more sedate and castigate temper, and came a great deal nearer the pure <hi>Adamical</hi> Crasis, than ours; and upon this Hypothesis, he might remain free from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54939:29"/> the vile deformities of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> necessarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on our Souls, the <hi>Sanguine, Cholerick, Phlog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick,</hi> and <hi>Melancholy</hi> Principles, whose uneven mixtures and complications in us, dispose us to vice, and betray us to disorder, met in his complexion in just proportions, and an equilibrious ponderancy; so that he felt not the inconveniencies of their intestine struglings, and pugnacious dimications, nor of the tyrannical puissance of one above the rest; for being fitly tempered, they subsided peacably within him, and dwelt together in an amicable concord; and though he could evocate them as he listed, to the ministry of their proper functions, and cause them as he pleased, to serve the ends of Godliness, and purposes of the Spirit; yet they never offered to break forth into vile and brutish displaies of themselves, or to shoot up into any unhandsom and peccant efflorescencies; so that though the Holy JESUS had such a concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scence planted in him, as is connatural to humanity, and alwayes grows up in an inseparable coalition with it (such as <hi>Adam</hi> had in the state of his Innocence) yet he might be far enough from all uncomely desires and appetites, sinful and exorbitant.</p>
               <p>Or if this be not enough, I may farther add, that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, GOD as well as Man: That he was united to the second Hypostasis of the <hi>Triune</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity; and thereby became of so extraordinary and sublimated an Holiness, that though his suscepted Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were of the same constitution with ours, yet he could very well extinguish, and subdue those pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inordinacies of it, from whence <hi>Original</hi> Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions flow; and with as much ease by his superlative and prevailing sanctity, work a thorow subaction and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54939:30"/> compescation of them, to keep his Soul from Sin; as he could by his Power, <hi>Metamorphose</hi> the Figuration of his Visage, to save his Person from violence.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The sum of all is this; <hi>Adam</hi> so long as he was Innocent, was incomparably happy; but when he sinned his Fall superinduced a miserable alteration on his Body: And whereas before it was of a delicate, even, and commendable temper, it made it cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and unruly, and sadly procreative of tumultuous motions, protervous passions, turbulent affections, and vagrant desires in his Spirit; from his Loins issued our Bodies, which being made of <hi>Adams,</hi> were of the same degenerate nature with it; and consequently occasioned the like irregularities, and fatal tendencies to <hi>illicit</hi> things in our Souls, as soon as they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused into them, which are truly and properly <hi>Original Sin:</hi> And thus the method or way of its wide diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and <hi>oecumenick</hi> contagion (without the help of <hi>Praeexistence</hi> to evolve and unravel the difficulties of it) is rendred obvious and explicit, and that without any rude and indecorous justling, with GOD'S in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable <hi>Equity;</hi> for admitting crazed Bodies, to be the Seat and deferent of them <hi>(i. e.</hi> of those virulent influences which provoke and kindle them) it is as easy to understand, how untoward Passions, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malous dispositions, should be traduced from <hi>Adam</hi> to his Sons, as it is to conceive how morbifick qualities, should pass from <hi>Ancestors</hi> to <hi>Posterity,</hi> and any distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per prove <hi>Haereditary.</hi> If therefore there be no farther use to be made of the <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> than intelligibly to enucleate this perplexed circumstance, the epidemick and unbounded vagation of <hi>Original Guilt,</hi> through the Souls of Men, and to facilitate the explanation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54939:30"/> of it; we need not adopt it into the <hi>Articles</hi> of our Faith, nor rank it amongst the indispensable <hi>Credenda</hi> of our Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The Fourth Argument for Praeexistence, from Mens various <hi>Inclinations.</hi> 2. That these can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not proceed from any tinctures, imbided in a <hi>Former Life;</hi> for two Reasons. 3. But are advenient from the <hi>Body, Custome,</hi> or <hi>Education.</hi> 4. Or it may be from an occult and inobserved <hi>Principle,</hi> which is safe to Conclude.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. I Pass now to another Argument, whereby the Favourers of Praeexistence, would legitimate their Phansie, and Court us into a credit of their Hypothesis: It is raised from the <hi>variety of humane Dispositions,</hi> in reference to Speculations and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices; and is set down to this sense. That Mens <hi>inward</hi> complexions, are as discolor as their <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>outward;</hi> and the Crasis of their Minds, as multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, as those of their Bodies; that as their are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>radical</hi> Tempers, proper to their Corporal parts; so their are <hi>Mental</hi> and <hi>Animary</hi> Propensions, congenite with their Souls, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they descend Sealed and impregnated into the World. Thus it is easy to note, that some Men are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54939:31"/> strangely prone to some opinions; that they hastily grasp and catch at them, and greedily flie and fasten on them, at their very first Proposal: Whereas on the contrary; others, every whit as Learned as they; of as nimble parts, and solid Judgments, and spritely apprehensions, <hi>haesitate</hi> and boggle at them; and though they be stated to them with an equal clearness, and backt with the same convincing evidences, yet they can by no means approve and relish them, but are utterly and incurably set against them, and their aversness to them seems to be complicated and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the very frame and contexture of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Now from whence springs this intellectual Congruity to some <hi>Dogmata,</hi> and <hi>coyness</hi> and <hi>antipathy</hi> to others, unless their Souls <hi>Praeexisted,</hi> and so slid down into this state; praepossessed with intire affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to some Principles, and an ingrafted <hi>odium</hi> unto others?</p>
               <p>And the like is observable of the <hi>Geniusses</hi> of Men; that they eagerly propend to peculiar imployments, and are strongly vergent to particular exercises; of which native determinations, and congenerous ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, no tollerable Accompt can be given; but that their Souls trod another Stage, before they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on this, and were there addicted to some kind of Transactions, analogous to these which they here affect; and being much delighted with, and long habituated to them then, they still retain some little touches, strictures, and reliques of them; and as their Reason and Faculties, mature and ripen, are here awakened into a fresh choice, renewed Love, and postlimineous recovery of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But against these confident allegations it may be <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54939:31"/> considered; First, how the fore-mentioned propensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are not <hi>Ʋniversal,</hi> and blended with the consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>every</hi> Person; but are thin sown and grow up sparsedly, here and there a <hi>few,</hi> and as for the Generalitie of People, they are strangers to them, and feel nothing of their strength and praevalence: For where there are <hi>five</hi> naturally bent to any one kind of Craft, and remarkably taken with any spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Notions; there are as many <hi>Millions</hi> that are free to all, indifferent to the reception of any, that are first and upon best grounds recommended to them; and this seems to null and evacuate the foregoing Ratiocinations, which at first view appeared so ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and forcible: For if some descend into this life, bigg with aptnesses and proclivities to peculiar Arts and Theories; why then should not all (supposing they Praeexisted together) do the like? For then they could not but be devoted every one, to some certain speculations and imployments in that condition; and these having gained there affections there, their Souls should be stamped with permanent aptitudes to them, and as soon as they are capable of it upon Earth, should alwayes break out into vehement pronesses, and delightfull essayes to those Opinions and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, which are most consimilous and proportionate, to such as they were Ancient admirers, and Practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of: But common experience proves it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and well assures us that very <hi>few</hi> have a natural, and ingenite kindness, for one Notion or Exercise above another; but are alike prompt to all, and can close affectionately with <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> or any that comes next, and sollicits their complyance upon fairest terms, and most rational accompts; which makes me strongly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54939:32"/> surmise, that mens spontaneous forwardnesses, and complacent leanings to determinate Objects, in this present state, are not reviviscencies, of any Predis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions they had to analogous instances in a former; for then they would not be so <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>infrequent</hi> as they are; but <hi>all</hi> as well as <hi>some,</hi> would phansie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Notions and Professions, and we should see every one by nature inclining to such Theories and Practices, as are most agreeable to those they were heretofore inured to.</p>
               <p>But then again, there are several things here below, which the <hi>Geniusses</hi> of men pursue and follow with the hottest chase, that can have nothing in the upper Regions to typifie or resemble them, in the least sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of anologie; as <hi>Planting, Building, Husbandry,</hi> the <hi>working of Manufactures,</hi> &amp;c. Thousands drink in the Love of these, together with their Parents milk, and are enamoured on them from their very Cradles; yet I am sure the affectations of these Arts, cannot be derived from <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> they cannot possibly be any new expergefactions of dormient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensions, or reflorescencies of obsolete and forgotten Customs, contracted in a superior life; because there is nothing parallel to them above, about which <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>existent</hi> Spirits could be busied: For who is so phran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or foolish, as to dream <hi>Gardening, Brick-laying Agriculture, Weaving,</hi> &amp;c. Or any callings like them, to be in fashion in the <hi>Coelestial</hi> Countries? And if Men may have natural desires, and radicated inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to those exercises, which they could not take any cognoscence of, nor of any thing answerable to them, in the state of <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> it is plain that all the propensities originally planted in them, were not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54939:32"/> brought from thence: And if not all, what necessity of granting that any were? (For where some took their Rise, the rest might do so too) and if none were drawn from thence, then he that goes about to prove <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> by this variety of Humane inclinations, argues from a false <hi>Topick,</hi> and his Reasonings are ill applyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But when I disprove one, it will be expected, that I should assign another cause of these pretty ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and point out something else as a likely Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to give Life and Being to them: And methinks none stands so fair for this office as the <hi>Body,</hi> whose influence must questionless have a great stroke, in the causation of these dissimulous propensities; that it can produce effects cognate and equivalent to these, and so probably these also, is most apparent.</p>
               <p>From whence springs the odd diversitie of Mens <hi>Palates</hi> and <hi>Appetites?</hi> This Mans meat (as the <hi>Diverb</hi> runs) is another Mans poison; that which I love and rellish with the highest gust, my Companion perfectly abhors, and cannot indure to put it in his mouth, nor may be to touch it with his fingers: And again, what he deemeth most delicious, is to me as odious; and the very thought of his appetitious Dish, cloggs my stomach with a <hi>nausea,</hi> and provokes to squeamish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and loathings; that which the Father dotes on, the Son abominates; and what the Master accompts most pure <hi>Ambrosia,</hi> the Servant heartily detests; and it moves no more longings in him, than if it were a Mess of condited <hi>Night-Shade,</hi> or a Cup of lethiferous <hi>Aconite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence come our different Judgments in <hi>Hearing?</hi> That which is ravishing melody to me, is an ugly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54939:33"/> noise, and offensive grating to him that stands next; and what my Friend esteems the most exquisite and delightfull Harmony, moves me to nothing but distast and anger: With what raised passion, and attentive wonder, do some receive those despicable sounds, of which disdain makes others heedless, and stops their Ears with deafness to them? So have I known some, listen to the wild modulations of the <hi>Canorous Thrush,</hi> as if he chaunted <hi>Anthems;</hi> and cry up garrulous <hi>Progne,</hi> Summers Pedissequent, for a perfect <hi>Siren:</hi> Others I have seen admire the coactions of sallacious <hi>Frogs;</hi> and applaud the inharmonious rehearsals of the one-ton'd <hi>Cuckow,</hi> as well composed consorts: Some envy the <hi>Crane</hi> for his harsh vociferations, more than <hi>Philoxenus</hi> did for his extended Neck; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers marvell as much, at the scurvy Hollowings of the Weak-ey'd <hi>Owl,</hi> as the <hi>Birds</hi> do at her mopish Visage, when she peeps abroad by Day-light: Some prefer the inauspicious crocitations of the raucous <hi>Night-Raven,</hi> before sweet-noted <hi>Philomela's</hi> Musick, and the pleasantest Ditties of the winged <hi>Choristers;</hi> and others had rather attend to the ruefull yawlings of <hi>Juno's</hi> Bird, prinkt up with varicolour gayeties, the spoils of drowzie <hi>Argus;</hi> than the farewell Tunes of the solitary <hi>Swan,</hi> when sitting on his watry Hearse, he Sings his own <hi>Dirge's:</hi> Some again value the <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe-Drone,</hi> above the Altisonous <hi>Organ,</hi> and others had as live hear the dolesome threnes of departing <hi>Clinicks,</hi> or piteous out-Cries of vagient <hi>Infants,</hi> as a Lesson on the <hi>Lute</hi> or <hi>Dulcimer.</hi> But not to be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that which to one Mans hearing is Pleasant, to anothers is intollerable.</p>
               <p>And the like may be said of the rest of the <hi>Senses:</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54939:33"/> Some hate the most <hi>Aromatick</hi> Odours, as much as the <hi>Fumigations</hi> of the Death-Bed: Others have had their Skins blistered with the touch of a <hi>Rose,</hi> as if it had been a Plaister of <hi>Cantharides:</hi> And others again have swooned at the sight of wholsome <hi>Diet;</hi> and that which should have releiv'd their <hi>Spirits,</hi> has af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them with a <hi>Syncope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is the cause I say, that we affect these things so diversly (our Souls being all alike) but only that our <hi>Bodies</hi> differing a little in their respective Craseis or Composures, strangely vary our <hi>Sensations?</hi> And if the <hi>Body</hi> can thus cause us, to <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> Sensibles; why not as well to <hi>Approve,</hi> and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellish</hi> Trades, and Sciences, which are conversant about them?</p>
               <p>How easy is it to conceive (me-thinks) that he, whose Crasis favours <hi>Judgment,</hi> should delight in the Rimation of Natures Secrets, and the Studies of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siologie,</hi> wherein that Faculty is so usefull? And that another, whose Constitution is advantageous unto <hi>Phansie,</hi> should take a special liking unto <hi>Musick, Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Poetry,</hi> and <hi>Romancing,</hi> where Invention is so concerned? And that a Third, whose Temperament is perfective of <hi>Memory,</hi> should fall in Love with <hi>Arithmatique, Historiography,</hi> and <hi>Chronology,</hi> which a tenacious Reminiscency renders most facil and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable? And that a Fourth, excelling in none of these Properties, should be indifferently given to any of these Studies, and able by an Ingenuous sedulity, to gain a competent Knowledge in them all? And from some influence of the <hi>Body</hi> it may very well be, (especially if <hi>Custom,</hi> or <hi>Education</hi> be found in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with that Corporal praedominance) that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54939:34"/>
                  <hi>Aesculapius, Mars, Vulcan,</hi> &amp;c. Should have their proper <hi>Devoto's,</hi> and Zealous <hi>Sectators.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea farther, it seems very probable to me, that the <hi>Corporeal</hi> part, should sway the <hi>Mind</hi> in reference to repudiating, or embracing the sublimest, and most abstracted Notions; whether of <hi>Mathematicks, Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>physicks,</hi> or <hi>Theology:</hi> Who knows not that the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the <hi>Intellect,</hi> and the perfection of <hi>Reason,</hi> depend much upon the Fabrick, and modification of Mens Organs? That some are perfect <hi>Innocents,</hi> and <hi>Ideots,</hi> and others stupid <hi>Dunces,</hi> and invincible <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants,</hi> meerly from the imperfection of those alone? And if the Frame of the <hi>Body,</hi> by its redundancy or defectiveness, can thus pervert the Understanding, and after the clearness and perspicacity thereof; I think we may well pronounce it, the likely occasion of those free intellectual compliances, and shie aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations, which shew themselves in different Persons, to the same <hi>Opinions;</hi> for every one must conclude concerning them, according to their own <hi>Idea's</hi> and perceptions of them: And the apprehensions of some, by reason of the rectitude of their <hi>Bodies,</hi> being more quick and penetrative; and those of others, because of the depravedness of the same, hebete and torpid; hence it happens, that some on their first hearing, are passionate <hi>Amorists</hi> of those <hi>Dogmata,</hi> which before they were unacquainted with, they instantly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending their pulchritude and rationality; while others, are fain to suspend their assent for a long time, and cannot become their hearty <hi>Proselytes,</hi> till they have more throughly sifted their warrantableness and solidity; and so by a slack and tardigradous progress, finally arrive at the approbation of them.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:54939:34"/>
               <p>But when all perplexities are quite unfolded, and difficulties removed, and obscurities banished, and the presented Theories are laid naked and bare to the understandings of Men, and reason pleads for their admission into the affections; if then they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not embrace and love them, but still (when their truth and sincerity, is as clear as the <hi>Meridian</hi> Sun) repulse and shun them; yet neither does this at all evince, that their Souls sunk down hither out of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, prepossessed with any prejudicies, against the proposed speculations: For this there scrupulosity and irreconcileableness to them, may arise purely from those anticipations, and preconceptions, which <hi>Custome</hi> and <hi>Education</hi> have instiled into them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their affections are so insnared, and captivated with extreme fondness to adverse Principles, that they cannot for their lives, discard their old Favourites, to take in novel Sentiments in their room, though they have much greater reason to be kindly entertained, than those glozing <hi>Sycophants,</hi> and less veracious Principles, which have so long been the welcome <hi>Guests.</hi> Custome we know is a second Nature; and if once absurdities come to be naturalized, by use and education; it will be hard to eradicate them, and to disabuse the mind from those prepossessions she labours under, though never so nonsensical and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: And if it be hard to emancipate the thoughts, when servilely inslaved to false <hi>Prolepses;</hi> it must upon the same score be difficult also, to make them fasten upon genuine apprehensions of those things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they have hitherto been misperswaded: For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinions cannot dwell together in the same mind at once; we must therefore be divorced from the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54939:35"/> false, before we can be espoused to the true; and if a Customary dilection of spurious notions, makes the first work uneasy, it must necessarily make the latter so too: Wherefore we need not ascribe our perverse reluctancies, to close with palpable Truths, to any congenial dislikes or incongruities to them, born into the World with us; but only to our non-intellections of them; or else to our familiarity, and long addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedness to opposite Doctrines, whereby we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and holden in an inexpugnable disaffection of them: And for the farther confirmation of this, I challenge any Man to speak, when ever he met with an Ingenious <hi>Philosopher,</hi> and propounded a rational maxime to him, in prejudice of which he never read, nor heard, nor observed any thing; and he did not readily own it, and without the least tergiversation amicably fall in and comply with it, notwithstanding his stiffest natural indispositions thereunto; provided that he had full, and right conceivings of it?</p>
               <p n="4">4. But when all is done, if this <hi>Hypothesis</hi> proves too weak and narrow, to bottom these <hi>Phaenomena</hi> upon; if the influence of the <hi>Body, Custome</hi> and <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> will not satisfactorily explicate, the great diversity of mens insitous vergencies and propensions; they may then be imputed to a <hi>secret Causality,</hi> and pronounced the effects of a <hi>Latent</hi> and <hi>incognite Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple:</hi> And though this may seem less <hi>Philosophical,</hi> yet I am sure it is a far safer Course, than to deduce them from <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> for thus we do but modestly confess our own Blindness and Ignorance, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at last the Studies of the Ingenuous, may illigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and abolish; whereas they that <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Wrong,</hi> will make <hi>Praeexistence</hi> the source of these inclinations,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54939:35"/> and think they have thereby compleatly solved them; run themselves upon bigger Prejudicies, and become guilty of the <hi>Tinkers</hi> error, that in mending one hole, makes two; for while by this means, they (in their own apprehensions) bolt one door against a Rout of <hi>Absurdities,</hi> they fling open another to numerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, and let in such a train and rabble of <hi>audacious</hi> Errors, as do not only tumult and mutiny amongst themselves, to the great disparagement of the <hi>Hypothesis;</hi> but daringly confront the <hi>Churches</hi> Authority, and rudely insolence <hi>Religion</hi> her self, contemerating her hallowed <hi>Institutions.</hi> This charge I might make good, by a large Enumeration of the <hi>Antistaechal,</hi> or inconsistent Notions coincident with <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> and its huge disconformities to the HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY CHURCH, in her professed Doctrines; but the digression would be too tedious and unseasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; I forbear it therefore, and go on where I left.</p>
               <p>I say then, if our bodily Tempers, and the Usages and Assuefactions of <hi>Life,</hi> in which we have been trained up and nurtured, seem not <hi>adaequate</hi> Causes, of our different Inclinations and <hi>Geniusses;</hi> we may securely believe there is something else, though we connot positively determine what, that is concurrent to the production of them: And for my own part, I am half perswaded, that the same active Principle which Rules in the diversimodous Nidulations of <hi>Birds;</hi> and elegant Glomerations of Industrious <hi>Silk-Worms,</hi> that directs Ingenious <hi>Arachne,</hi> in her pretty Weavings, and prompts laborious Insects, in rearing their mellifluous Combs: That guides the <hi>Brutes</hi> to such peculiar Games; and instructs them in the crafty insidiations of their Preys: That sows the Seeds of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54939:36"/>
                  <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Enmity,</hi> between things void of Passion; in <hi>Kind</hi> and <hi>Amorous</hi> Sympathies, and <hi>cross, discor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant,</hi> fell Antypathies. Some such thing I say (though I cannot think it that Prodigious <hi>Hobgoblin,</hi> the <hi>Spirit of Nature)</hi> which produceth these strange effects; where the <hi>Genius</hi> is naturally bent to any special <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cercise,</hi> may put a Bias in the Phansie, and wind and draw it to the same.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. A Fifth Argument, from the <hi>Praeexistence</hi> of the <hi>Messiah's</hi> Soul; 2. Refuted.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THE Next Argument to confirm the <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> is the <hi>Praeexistence of our Saviours Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
                  </label> His Soul (say our <hi>Antagonists)</hi> was in Being long before he assumed Flesh, and actuated a <hi>Terrestrial</hi> Body: He appeared to the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of Old, and transacted with <hi>Moses,</hi> about freeing <hi>Israel</hi> from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bondage; and when he had broken the Yoke of their intollerable Thraldom, and led them into liberty; he gave them a Law from Heaven, and became their Mighty Patron and Protector, all along governing and conducting them, in their tedious Marches to the Land of <hi>Promise.</hi> And least this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentation should fail of success, and be rejected as an empty Fiction, and vain Conjecture, of the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siful and Opinionative; it is backt with a number of Holy Scriptures, and there is scarce a Text in the sacred Book, which speaks of his Deserting his Glory,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54939:36"/> his Descent from above, his Profection from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his Return to him again; but is deemed an authentick evidence of this Supposition, that the Soul of JESUS existed before his Incarnation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now not to squabble about the truth of this <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> (which is very doubtfull) I shall quickly yield, that the Soul of CHRIST was long extent, before it was Incarnate. But then certainly this is a very rotten and lubricous Foundation, for a <hi>General Praeexistence;</hi> and to conclude that from hence, would be an Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence guilty of shamefull presumption and inconse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: For there are divers ponderous Reasons for our LORD'S <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which cannot be alledged for ours.</p>
               <p>As First; He was the incomparable and peerless Favourite of the GOD-HEAD, and immeasurably indeared to the HOLY TRIAD: He was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the BELOVED <hi>Son,</hi> and was affected by <note place="margin">Mat. 3. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ult.</note> the DIVINITY, with an infinite tenderness, such as no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> meer <hi>Man,</hi> no nor the loftiest <hi>Angel</hi> must expect; and being thus highly advanced in the Divine Love, no marvell if he were dignified with extraordinary Kindnesses, and raised to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of such matchless <hi>Prerogatives</hi> (of which <hi>Praeexistence</hi> might be one) as were never to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged to the common sort of Mortals.</p>
               <p>Again, one prime End of his Mission hither, was to suffer bitter and terrible things, for the Sons of Men; he was to be despised and mocked, persecuted and betrayed, slandered and reviled, spit upon and buffeted; he was to be falsly accused, unjustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and ignominiously Crucified: And on his Cross he was to bear the Sins of all the World; and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54939:37"/> to grapple with the wrath of an incensed Deity; and to sustain the heavy malediction of the Law; and to be made a <hi>Victim</hi> to his Fathers JUSTICE, and a perfect <hi>Holocaust</hi> to expiate our high offences, and attone the Majesty of Heaven to us; it was but just therefore that he should <hi>Praeexist,</hi> that so these his Passions might be ushered in with a <hi>praevious</hi> Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and that he might possess the Beatitude of the <hi>Caelestial</hi> Life, as an <hi>Ante-praemium,</hi> to sweeten and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviate his ensuing Miseries.</p>
               <p>But then besides (for I Study brevity) it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite he should <hi>Praeexist</hi> upon another accompt; namely, that he might be the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Husband</hi> of the CHURCH, to instruct and guide it, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intend and moderate the affairs of it; that so those Souls, which were in the End, to be bought with the effusion of his Blood, might from the beginning, be ruled by his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> and live under his Tutelary Care and Providence.</p>
               <p>So that grant our <hi>Redeemer</hi>'s Soul to have <hi>Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted;</hi> yet there being not the same Reasons for us to do as he did; his <hi>Praeexistence</hi> cannot be Conclusive of ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:54939:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. Another Argument for Praeexistence, from the great <hi>Right</hi> it does the <hi>ALMIGHTY,</hi> consisting of two Branches. 2. The first Branch urged, 3. And answered. 4. The second Branch urged, 5. And answered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. A Sixth Argument which stands up for Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence, and offers to maintain its Interest, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers it self to this effect; That <hi>it speaks more true and</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>honourable things of GOD, than the Hypothesis of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Creation;</hi> and does not bespatter him with such foul indignities, as that prophanely throws upon him; but clearly wipes off all ill-favour'd Dotches, and uncomely Macula's, wherewith it slurs his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est purity, and denigrates the whiteness, and sullies the splendor of his Glory; so that the Plea divides it self into two Branches: Let us see how each is vibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted against the commune Hypothesis, and how that behaves it self in the rencounter, so as to come off in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulnerate: for the grand design of this Argument, is to subvert the opinion of <hi>Immediate Creation,</hi> and then to triumph in its overthrow, erecting Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence on the ruines of it. Which</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the First place, is conceived (by such as would have it do so) to utter most <hi>Truth</hi> of GOD; for it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately <note place="margin">1. Br<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urg. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> coheres with his own Declaration, of resting
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54939:38"/> from his Work on the Seventh Day, and according to the Tenor of inspired Testimony, consigns his Creative operations, within the space of the first Hebdomade: after which, his Power of making Creatures ceased to act, and retired into himself for ever, celebrating an <hi>Holy Sabbath,</hi> never to terminate or expire; and though it hath been ever since imployed in susteining the Universe, and the various essences therein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in managing the same, in conformity to the Rules of exactest Prudence; yet it hath alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted from new productions, and hath hitherto super-added nothing, to those primitive Substances, to which the first Senarie, or six dayes space, allotted being. This as the HOLY GHOST by the infallible Pen, of his first and great Amanuensis teacheth, was GOD'S method in fabricating the World, he made all things together in the Beginning, and never augmented them by an after Creation: and this plausibly argues the truth of Praeexistence, that it is so concinnous, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry accommodate to the sacred Story of the Creation, allowing GOD to have compleated the same in his six dayes Work, and then to change his Labour into eternal Rest. Whereas if we take up the General Faith, we must believe quite another thing; that GOD did not put a period to his Works, and inchoate his Rest at six dayes end, according to Scripture evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the express declaration of the Spirit in that behalf; but is daily busied in Creating Souls, which imployment he seems to have resigned thousands of years ago.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To this I briefly rejoyn, that the Opinion of Souls <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> immediate creation, as to the Instance given, complies as fairly with the mind of the Bible, as Praeexistence
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54939:38"/> does: And as that releaseth GOD from his Works, at the end of six dayes, so does this, though with a lawful Difference; for whereas that binds him to cease from Creating at all, after the term of six Dayes; this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth that after that time he acquiesced from creating <hi>new Species</hi> only, but alloweth him still to multiply some of their <hi>Individuals,</hi> according to his own Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placiture; nor needs this hinder him from sanctifying a perpetual <hi>Sabbath</hi> in himself; for if as great a work as this be competible to his declared Rest, this may be consistent with it; and we all know, that though he Rests for ever, yet he is daily active in regenerating souls, which is as great a Work as daily to create them, and therefore it is stiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the subject of it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; so that for ought appears, the Hypothesis of Daily Creation belies the Deity as little as Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence. But they complain it <hi>dishonours</hi> him more; how justly will be seen, when we have heard the Charge drawn up against it, and its own Apologie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Accusation is framed after this sort; that it <note place="margin">2. B<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urg.</note> puts the Majesty on high to <hi>very servile and unworthy Offices,</hi> and tasks him to such homely and invenust im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, as are scarce consistent with his verecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Holiness: for if that be true, when ever the lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious consent to uncleanness, and are pleased to joyn in unlawful mixtures and embraces, GOD is forced to stand a Spectator of their vile impurities, and to assist their bestial pleasures, with no less than a special act of Creation; then when ever any lustful Mates combine to gratifie their vitious Passions, and unite in shameful and forbidden Copulations, Omnipotence it self must stoop from its Throne, to attend their unholy practices, and rain down showers of Souls from above,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54939:39"/> to actuate the Emanations of their base Concupiscence, and all this to a goodly purpose: lest Natures Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments should miscarry, and the Rudiments and Incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of life, laid by venereous Wantons, should prove effoete and perish. And is not this a fine seemly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking for the Great JEHOVAH? to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Libidinous in their Fornications, Adulteries, Incests, and Buggeries; and to ingage his Power in Creating Souls, to animate those vital preparations, which their detestable filthiness ministers? Should we study for ever to disgrace him, and to confront his loftiness and purity, by an indigne exercise, what could we task him to, more sordid and inglorious?</p>
               <p>And moreover it condemns him of <hi>strange oversight and insipience,</hi> and supposeth him to act very ineptly in many Cases; in that he often includes the Souls of men in inconvenient Habitations, and sentenceth them to monstrous and mishapen Bodies, notwithstanding he was well aware of the supervening obliquities, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities; this, were it true, would be no small scandal to his unbounded Sapience. But here again Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence vindicates him to the full; for that transfers the fate of the afflicted Spirits, upon <hi>Secondary Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> and blames their Exorbitancies and miscarriages, for framing their Bodies so imperfect and anomalous, and then for drawing them down into them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. These are the black and opprobrious Calumnies, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> which onerate the Hypothesis of Souls <hi>immediate Creation,</hi> in the second place: It sacrilegiously detracts from GODS infinite Holiness, and foully blemisheth his perfect Wisdom; but it is chargeable with nothing less than these reproachful Characters; and deserves them no more, than that other Opinion, for the justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54939:39"/> and establishment of which, it is thus aspersed. What dehonestation of GOD'S Integrity, can pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly result from his providing Souls for spurious Issues, more than for those of a legall Generation? He gave Mankind a Power of begetting their like, after such a manner; and when by virtue of this Power, their spermatick Principles are sitted for animation, he is determined by his own Goodness (which from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning prescribed him such an oeconomy, or method of acting) to infuse Souls into them: And when he comes to supply their prolifique substances, with Souls from himself, he regards not their procreative Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, whether they were lawfull or not; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siders them barely in their <hi>Natural</hi> respects, and so can with as much Honour, and as little infamy to his own Sacredness, prepare Souls for illegitimate <hi>Faetusses,</hi> as for those of an honester propogation: For he looks upon them as devested of all <hi>Moral</hi> Circumstances, and as the pure <hi>Natural</hi> Fruits, of that harmless Faculty, which He at first implanted in his Creatures. 'Tis true, if People abuse this Faculty, and make it inservient to dishonest Procreations; in this there is filthiness and shame enough (because the thing is diametrically opposite to the Laws of <hi>Chastity,</hi> which should be kept inviolate) but then the ignominy and pollution lights upon the Criminals only, and though GOD furnisheth the illicit Conceptions, with Souls inspired from above; yet in thus doing, he is as clean from all dedecorous conspurcations and defilements, as if they were legitimate off-springs of the Conjugal Bed: For he eyes them only in their <hi>Physical</hi> habitudes, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities; in reference to which they are no way sinful, nor can GOD'S attendance on them be dishonourable;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54939:40"/> so that this Argument against immediate Creation, might as well have been urged from his vigilance o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Innocent,</hi> as <hi>Ʋnlawful</hi> Coitions; they being both alike, so far as they are <hi>Natural,</hi> and so far as he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddles with them, when he formeth Souls to vivifie the productions of them: But as our Adversaries deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the <hi>First,</hi> a convenient Topick, so neither do I the <hi>Latter;</hi> for if it be duely searched, it will be found, to cast as little indignity, and prophanation upon GOD, as <hi>Praeexistence</hi> it self. To illustrate this, imagine GOD should Create one Soul, and as soon as He had done, instantly pop it into a base-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Body: And then Create another, the matter of an hours space before its praecipitation into such a Receptacle: Which of these actions, would be most diminutive of the Creators Honour? Would not the difference be insensible, and the scandal, if any, the same in both? Yet thus lies the case just, betwixt <hi>Praeexistentiaries</hi> and <hi>Ʋs:</hi> We say GOD inliveneth the genital Seed of voluptuous <hi>Carnalists,</hi> with new Created Souls: They hold, they were made some thousands of Ages agoe; which in respect of GOD, and the <hi>Eternity</hi> he injoyes, was not an hour before: Which of these <hi>Tenets</hi> now, conciliates most veneration to our Maker? Do they not both speak things equally <hi>worthy,</hi> or <hi>unworthy</hi> of Him? And if both favour him alike, what a doughty Argument is this, to vouch the Interest of <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> above the other <hi>Hypothesis;</hi> by telling us it allows more honourable apprehensions of GOD, than <hi>That?</hi> What does it speak of him, but what it well beseems himself to own, and every Good Man to beleive concerning Him? Admit that his watchfull Providence, waits upon dissolute volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54939:40"/> in their unmeet conjunctions, and sends down fresh Created Spirits, to actuate their obscaene Emissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; what is here done, which is not very high and becoming GOD, and most congruous and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate, to his immense Grandeur and Majesty? For in the First place, his Condescention is hereby made signal and eximious: He is Gloriously humble beyond a Parallel; and by his own example, Lessons us to perform the meanest Works, if fit and profitable; and to be content even to drudge for the common Benefit of the World. And Secondly, hereby he elicits <hi>Good</hi> out of <hi>Evill,</hi> causing famous and Heroick Persons, to take their Origin from base occasions; and so converts the Lusts of sensual <hi>Varlets,</hi> to nobler Ends than they designed them. And then Thirdly, hereby he often detects the lewdness of Sinners, which otherwise would be smothered; and brings them to condigue punishment, which otherwise would be evaded; and makes their exemplary penance and infamy, a notable Corrective to the like vices in them, that otherwise would commit them. Now are not all these actions and concerns (to be illustriously condescensive; to bring Good out of Evill; to discover, punish, and prevent Sin) very graceful and agreeable unto GOD? Yet to intitle him to these offices, is all the dishonour our <hi>Hypothesis</hi> does him; and therefore I hope, it credits him as much as its invidious Rival, <hi>Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I had almost forgotten the other noted blemish, wherewith it is said to avile and criminate him: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>imprudence</hi> and <hi>stolidity;</hi> for if GOD creates all Souls, just before they are united unto Bodies, he must incorporate some in very incommodious Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54939:41"/> That is, where there Bodies are disfigured with greivous distortions, or cumbered with sad monstro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, or mutilated with unnatural deficiencies, or loden with superfluous protuberancies and excrescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; to think GOD should immure new Created Spirits, in such deformed and incongruent Bodies, would pend hard upon the Attribute of his Wisdom, and be very exitious to the Repute thereof.</p>
               <p>But I Answer in a word; He that can rescue himself from dormitation and prejudice, and with an adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and unbiass'd mind, rightly perpend this gloomy passage of the Divine Providence; will easily construe it to a better sense. Many of GOD'S <hi>Judgments</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, deep and inscrutable; and <hi>his Wayes</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, invious and investigable; and so may this be <note place="margin">Rom. 11. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> we are now discoursing: When he Creates the Souls of men, and immediately consigns to them ill-featur'd Mansions, there may be vast profundities of <hi>Wisdom</hi> in the Affair, which our shallow Natures cannot fathom: GOD may send these Judgments on some secret Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands, and important messages, to the afflicted par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or their nearest Relatives; and convince their Consciences why they came, though the World be unacquainted, with the purposes of their mission: Perhaps he may make them <hi>Heralds</hi> of his Anger, or <hi>Monitors</hi> of their sins, or <hi>Censers</hi> of their manners, to reprove and castigate those close <hi>Enormities,</hi> which never fell under publique Cognoscence; or to redress those apert Extravagancies, which are offensive unto every Eye: It may be he intends them for Ministers of Good, and Instruments of Mercy to them; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements to Virtue, and refraenations of Wantonness; for wholsome <hi>Alexicaca,</hi> and commodous absolutories
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54939:41"/> from sinful pravities, which otherwise might be more apt to incroach upon them; at least this good effect, they may accomplish upon all such as are spectators of them, and have their hearts touched with any sense of Piety and Religion: They cannot chuse but set them a glorifying GOD, and fill their mouths with the lowdest <hi>Hymns</hi> of Praise, and tune their hearts to the highest <hi>Key</hi> of gratitude, in consideration of their own bodily rectitude and indolence, and that natural symetrie and perfection, which adorns themselves. And since the inclusion of <hi>new</hi> Created Souls, in such ill contrived and disadvantageous Bodies, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon such excellent designs of Wisdom as these, and others also to us indiscernable; there is no reason, why GOD should be blasphemed with <hi>Ineptness</hi> in the Dispensation; or have his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in reference to it, called in question by insulse and maledicous blaterations.</p>
               <p>In <hi>fine</hi> therefore, this Argument Conludes nothing for <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> in as much as it does not discourse most plausibly of GOD: For the <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Creation, is every whit as veriloquous, and speaks as <hi>decorous</hi> things of Providence, as that, for all its bigg pretensions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:54939:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. Another Argument from the <hi>joynt suffrage of the Learned;</hi> 2. Answered. 3. Why <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Proofs</hi> are silently <hi>praetermitted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THE Last Argument for <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> which I shall take notice of, is founded upon the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>general consent of the Ancient Sophy;</hi> all which agree in the approbation of it, unanimously voting, and agnizing it to be true. It was the Opinion of the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Gymnosophists,</hi> the <hi>Persian Magi,</hi> the <hi>Indian Brachmans,</hi> the <hi>Jewish Rabbins,</hi> the <hi>Graecian Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> the <hi>British Druides,</hi> and some of the <hi>Christian Fathers:</hi> The <hi>Hebrew Sages</hi> made it a part of their <hi>Cabbala,</hi> and pretend it a Doctrine primarily delivered from their Great Legislator <hi>Moses;</hi> and being Stamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with such great and venerable Authorities, it must needs pass for a currant Truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But to stop the mouth of this <hi>Sonorous</hi> Allegation, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Confut. </seg>
                  </label> I Answer; that it makes an huge noise to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: Like a Cannon charg'd with Powder, it goes off with a loud report, but does no execution, because void of its murderous load.</p>
               <p>For First, I conceive that some of the fore-cited Sects, were Persons but <hi>indifferently Learned;</hi> their Renown did much exceed their Knowledge, and their Fame by far out-went their Wisdom: They were some of them perhaps, no better than flat <hi>Daemonolaters,</hi> in strict League with <hi>Diabolical</hi> Spirits, and maintained
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54939:42"/> too close an amity and familiar intercourse, with the <hi>Aereal</hi> Principality; and being favoured and abetted by them, they could by <hi>Theurgical</hi> Rites, and Inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, do strange feats, and amuse and awe the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by their Sorceries and Necromancies, Magical tricks and Praestigious collusions; but as for their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with sober Philosophy, 'tis like it was not over deep nor intimate; so that their Authority, is but a slender prop to underset <hi>Praeexistence</hi> withal.</p>
               <p>And in the Second place, that of the <hi>Circumcised Doctors,</hi> is not so strong as to bear it up by main force: For though they had the Law of GOD amongst them, and so had their Minds illightened with a purer sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than the Gentile <hi>Sophists;</hi> yet they were friends to many gross and monstrous Errors, of which in all likelihood this was one. The Sacred Volume informs us, that some of them peremptorily asserted, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>That there was neither Resurrection, nor Angel, nor Spirit.</hi> And <hi>Maimonides</hi> one of the principal Masters, beleived that Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, was the Prerogative of <hi>Just</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> Souls only; and as for the Impious, they perished together with their Bodies. And this <hi>R. Kimchi</hi> stoutly argues from those words in the first <hi>Psalm.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Ʋngodly shall not rise, or stand in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And because it is said in the 17. <hi>v.</hi> of 115. <hi>Psal.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Dead praise not the</hi> LORD, <hi>nor any that descend into silence, or the Grave:</hi> This forsooth he makes another Proof of it; and from the same Text he might as wisely have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that every ones Soul is Mortal, and extinct at Death, it being spoken of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Dead</hi> in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and not of the Improbous alone. And Cousin-German
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54939:43"/> to this was that notorious Mistake, which <hi>Elias Levita</hi> sets down, for the common Opinion of the <hi>Cabbalists,</hi> touching the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimation,</hi> called by them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or the <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Souls:</hi> For they Childishly conceited, that every Soul must be incorporated in three several Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and the Phansie they confirm with a proper testimony <hi>Job. 33. 29. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> See how God Worketh all these things thrice with Man:</hi> And because the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> contains the three Initial letters, of <hi>Adam, David, Messiah;</hi> from thence they vainly inferr, that these three, had but <hi>one</hi> Soul commune to them all, which first dwelt in <hi>Adam's</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then in <hi>Davids,</hi> and lastly in the <hi>Messiahs.</hi> A goodly conjecture, and as likely as that which would fetch an Indication of a <hi>Trinity,</hi> from the <hi>second</hi> word of <hi>Genesis</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> because it is compounded of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choative letters of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor did they only hold the transmigration of Souls, from one humane Body to another; but fondly imagined that they passed out of the Bodies of Men, into those of Birds and Brutes, as <hi>R. Bechai</hi> declares: To which odd and ridiculous Phansies, I shall adjoyn but one more as fond, and extravagant as the rest; I mean their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Revolution of the Dead;</hi> wherewith they were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally possest, firmly beleiving that all the Carcasses of the <hi>Jews,</hi> interred out of <hi>Palestine,</hi> should roll under ground into the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> that so they might rise in their own Country, at the day of Judgment, together with the rest of their Compatriots. Now they that could swallow all these absurdities, and hundreds besides, without chewing: Why should <hi>Praeexistence</hi> go against their Stomachs? Or what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54939:43"/> have we to take it up upon their credit, and to beleive it for a truth, because they taught it?</p>
               <p>Nor will its being a Branch of the <hi>Cabbala,</hi> free it from the suspicion of falshood, but rather make it more obnoxious to it: For that being delivered down by <hi>Oral</hi> tradition, from one to another, till the days of R. <hi>Jehuda;</hi> who is thought to have first collected it into Writing; no wonder if in so long a decurse of time, many counterfeit and subdititious things were foisted into it, and <hi>Praeexistence</hi> for one; all which he might publish for weighty truths, as thinking them primarily imparted from the mouth of <hi>Moses,</hi> though he never spent his breath, in recommending such nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacities to Posterity</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Graecian Philosophers,</hi> and <hi>Christian Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> that asserted <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> though they were worthy and famous Persons, yet their owning of the <hi>Tenet,</hi> is not enough to authorize and establish it: For they could speculate falsly as well as others, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize notorious Errors. Let any sober and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man, but seriously reflect upon the strange and garish whimsies, the toyish and absurd futilities, the silly and delirous fopperies of admirable <hi>Plato;</hi> who for his stupendious Learning and variety of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is all along of his <hi>Biographers,</hi> stiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: And now adored as a petty <hi>Numen,</hi> by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Philosophick</hi> Zealots of the present Age. And let him consider the enormous <hi>Dogmata</hi> of inclytous <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> who Wrote above Nine thousand Volumes, and before whom <hi>Plotinus</hi> himself, revering his prudence <note place="margin">Vid. Por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phyx. in vit. Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</note> and sagacitie, durst not continue his Lecture. And then let him speak, whether the best of <hi>Graecian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers,</hi> and the choicest of <hi>Christian Fathers,</hi> were
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54939:44"/> not very deceivable; and might not easily be mislead in this, as well as in other instances.</p>
               <p>Briefly therefore to apply a general Answer to the Argument: Admit it be an ancient Doctrine, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and maintained by renowned Schollars; yet this will hardly prove it true. For the greatest Clerks have faulty Pens, and Write not without their blots. The wisest Authors are but Men, and we know <hi>huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num est errare,</hi> by their Nature they are fallible, and made obnoxious to <hi>Hallucinations:</hi> So that for all their consenting to, and approving of, any such particular Notion or Opinion, it may still be false and erroneous. And that the most incomparable <hi>Virtuosoes,</hi> have had their slips and Errors, I might demonstrate by a large induction of Examples, and weary both my self and Reader with their numerositie; but let us take one for all, I mean <hi>Des-Cartes:</hi> And when I recollect his unlucky oversights, how he makes <hi>all Motion to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal;</hi> and holds the <hi>same Degree of it to be alwayes in the Ʋniverse;</hi> and confidently affirms that <hi>Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence it self can never effect a Vacuum;</hi> but above all, when I call to mind his internecine <hi>Hylolatry,</hi> and bloody dotage upon <hi>Matter,</hi> whereby he makes it to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and so opens a wide gap to <hi>Atheism;</hi> and at one blow massacres all the Brute-Animals in the World; supposing them to be meer <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Mechanical</hi> Engines, indued with no immaterial Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, but absolving all their Actions by virtue of the scite of their Organs, and confirmation of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; without the assistance of any Soul at all: And so treads counter to the mind of <hi>Pythagoras, Plato, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotle, Empedocles, Democritus, Porphyrie,</hi> and other noted Antiquities, who rightly contended that they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54939:44"/> had not only Souls, but Souls exalted to some degree of <hi>Rationality.</hi> When I say, I revolve in my thoughts the egregious failures of this Excellent <hi>Philosopher;</hi> and perceive his <hi>Placita</hi> to be so faulty and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: I cannot but conclude it hugely unsafe, to pin our Faith upon any mans sleeve; and that we have but little cause to acknowledge this <hi>Dogma</hi> for a Truth, because the <hi>Great ones</hi> so pronounce it.</p>
               <p>And now to draw towards a Conclusion. If there have been many of the Learned for <hi>Praeexistence;</hi> yet I am sure there have been as many of them, that never subscribed to it: So that putting in one against the other, we shall bring the Ballance to an even poize; and the Argument that seemed so very ponderous, will weigh just nothing at all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I should here take in hand the <hi>Scripture Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which are made to favour the Opinion: But I find the principal of them, dexterously Answered already by an Ingenious Pen; and therefore I shall spare my self that Labour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:54939:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The First <hi>Objection</hi> against <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> that it is Grounded upon odd presumption, of <hi>Heterogeneity</hi> in the Souls of Men; 2. Which is very <hi>incertain,</hi> 3. And also <hi>Improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> because attended with gross <hi>Absurdities.</hi> 4. The First <hi>Absurdity.</hi> 5. The Second. 6. The Third. 7. The Fourth. 8. The Fifth. 9. The Sixth.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. I Pass now to the Third and Last thing proposed; namely to give in such <hi>Objections</hi> against the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothesis,</hi> as my hasty thoughts shall suggest: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Cunctation of any praeliminary Ambages, the First shall be this: That it is built upon an incertain and unlikely <hi>Conjecture:</hi> It supposeth an <hi>Heterogeneity</hi> in the Soul of Man; that it consists of a primary sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and a Secondary emanative from that: Of a perceptive, and plastick part; in which latter resides a triple vital Congruity, to a three-fold Vehicle, <hi>viz. Aethereal, Aereal,</hi> and <hi>Terrestrial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now that this is a thing extreamly <hi>dubious,</hi> is manifest: For our acquaintance with Spirits is so little, and our ignorance of their Nature so great, that we can positively and certainly conclude no such matter concerning them. He that pretends to a graphical description, a punctual and explicit account, of their
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54939:45"/> Beings and Properties, does but fondly <hi>Platonize,</hi> in offering at that which is above his reach, and falls not within the compass of his abilities to perform: And when he hath beat his Brains, and wearied his Phansie, and tired himself in musing on the imaginary <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> of their Essence; and hath made a shift to coin some pretty Phantastick notions of it, and to connect them together in an handsom Method, and elegant contexture: Yet in the conclusion, all will amount but to a Philosophick <hi>Legend</hi> or <hi>Romance;</hi> which the Wise and Learned will as soon believe, as they will the famed Exploits of <hi>Don Quixot;</hi> or the pranks of noted <hi>Hudibras.</hi> The Man that attempts a distinct explication, of the Nature of the Soul in this life, does but tread a confounding Maze, and lose himself in a Labyrinth of difficulties; out of which there is no extrication: It is enough if in the next World, we have such a Clue of Knowledge put into our hands, as will guide us safely through the <hi>Maeandrian</hi> flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures, <hi>Anfractuous</hi> Circles, and <hi>Sinuous</hi> Nooks and <hi>Angulosities</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that there should be such an <hi>Heterogeneity</hi> in Humane Souls, as is confidently asserted; is more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over a thing very improbable; for it implies many prodigious <hi>Absurdities,</hi> a <hi>Specimen</hi> of which I shall next relate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. First, if the Souls of Men be made <hi>Heterogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and their Plastick part, be the Seat of a three-fold vital aptitude; this will charge GOD with great <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness</hi> to them, or unseemly <hi>oversight,</hi> in Creating them: Not becase by this frame of their Nature, they were made peccable (for a meer peccability, if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they had been invested with a power of retaining
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54939:46"/> their Innocence, would have been no injury to them) but because they were hereby obliged, and necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to transgress: Their Will was not so much in fault, that they revolted from GOD, as the structure and constitution of their Essence. Hear the Reviver of <hi>Origens</hi> Opinions, who speaks truth in the Case: <hi>They being originally made with a capacity, to join with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>count. Origen, <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. pag 49.</note>
                  <hi>this Terrestrial matter, it seems necessary according to the Course of Nature, that they should sink into it, and so appear Terrestrial Men.</hi> So that Men by the very mode and fashion of their Nature (supposing it indued with a triple Congruity of life) were constrained to unite with Earthly Bodies; and consequently to violate the Laws of Innocence, that so their capacity of living in conjunction, with Terrestrial substance, might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened and excited. For without antecedent obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and the practice of illicit things, no Soul ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hypothesis of <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> can become fit to actuate a fleshly Vehicle: For so long as the mind is unpolluted, and free from the contagion of Vice and Sin, the <hi>Aethereal</hi> Congruity maintains its Empire, binding up the Terrestrial one in a dormant condition, which nothing can let loose to domineer in the Soul, but vitiousness and immorality: So that if the <hi>Nature</hi> of Mankind, necessitated their union with <hi>Terrestrial</hi> matter, it did also as an indispensable Praeparative thereunto, necessitate their <hi>Lapse</hi> into Impiety. And if the GOD of Heaven Transacts at this rate with his Creatures; if he so contrives their Beings, as that the very <hi>Fabrick</hi> and <hi>Composure</hi> of them, irresistibly hales them into unrighteousness, and subjects them to sin and misery, I think for giving them such a Nature, He may well be said to act unkindly towards them, which he cannot do.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:54939:46"/>
               <p>Not will it mend the matter to say, he intended not that their Plastick powers, should <hi>involve</hi> them in so great misfortunes: For this were to accuse him of strange <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>inadvertency;</hi> as if when he formed Man, he did not mind or understand his Frame, but fixed a Principle in his Nature <hi>unawares,</hi> that he never meant should be exercised and made use of: Which yet at length exalting it self, against the Superior fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of his Soul, Naturally and Fatally plunged him into Sin, and an Union with the dorssiest Corporeity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Secondly, it makes one Created substance, <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerative</hi> and <hi>productive</hi> of the <hi>Essence</hi> of another; which in my apprehension is a thing impossible, it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly exceeding the Nature and Capacity of it, so to do. There is nothing that I can think on in the World, Omnipotence excepted; that can be the Efficient Cause of the Essence, of any substantial Being. 'Tis true the Sun is emissive of light, and the Fire of heat; but I hope none are so inconsiderate, as to take Light and Heat for substances: Yet this vast and admirable power of producing substantial Essence in it self, is ascribed to the Soul of Man, by the Hypothesis of its <hi>Heterogeneity.</hi> For if I rightly understand the Learned <note n="*" place="margin">See <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> More'<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. Book. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Chap. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Sect. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Author of the Notion, the <hi>Radical, Central, Primary,</hi> and <hi>Perceptive</hi> part of the Soul, is the object of Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But the secondary, and Plastick <hi>flows entirely</hi> from that, as an Emanative effect; and yet is held for a true and proper substance nevertheless. This to me is a thing very absurd and inconceivable, that one finite Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance should beget the Essence of another. But that which farther perplexeth the Mystery, and renders it more obscure and unintelligible is, that the Secondary substance of the Soul, <hi>differs widely</hi> from the Primary,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54939:47"/> though it be an immediate Emanation of it: For whereas the Primary part is <hi>Intelligent,</hi> and <hi>perceptive;</hi> the Secondary or Plastick, is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rtali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Book <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> C. 11. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 10.</note> destitute both of <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Sensation.</hi> And how this should come to pass, is another great Riddle: For if one Substance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth another by emanative Causality, the Substance so produced, must necessarily be an Emanation of the very Essence of the Efficient: And if it be an Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensial Emanation of it, it must be the very same with it (for the Essence of a thing cannot vary from it self) and consequently must have all those endowments, faculties, and perfections in it, which are existent in that. To affirm, the percipient part of the Soul can display it self in a <hi>substantial</hi> efflux, void of Sense; is methinks, just as if one should say, the <hi>Solar</hi> Orb can shine forth beams of Darkness, and hath a power of darting mid-night through the <hi>Hemisphere</hi> it resides in: For Darkness is not a more absolute privation of the Suns Excellence, which is Light, than senselessness is of the perfection of the Souls <hi>Central</hi> part, which is Rationality and Perception.</p>
               <p>And amongst other reasons, this is one, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swades me the Material World is not an <hi>Emanative Effect</hi> of the Deity; because then it must have been Homogeneal with the Divine Essence; and so not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but a Spiritual Substance. For that such a <hi>moles</hi> of Corporeity, should proceed from GOD, without any intermediate act of his, or any other Causality, but his bare Existence, considering he is a Spirit; and so in a principal Attribute of his Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriality, opposed unto Body, looks like a flat impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Thirdly, it overthrows the Article of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54939:47"/>
                  <hi>Resurrection:</hi> For no sooner does the Soul by death quit her Terrestrial habitation, but according to the tenour of this Hypothesis, she is incorporated in an <hi>Aerial Vehicle;</hi> and when her vital congruity to that expires, she is united to one of <hi>Aether.</hi> So that having once put off her carnal Body, she shall never be reinvested with it more: And though we are assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an infallible Word, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>This very Corruptible, shall put on incorruption;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>This very Mortal, shall put on immortality.</hi> Yet the vouchers of <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> as if they felt a degree of Inspiration, above the great <hi>Apostle,</hi> tell us bluntly there is no such matter. But though virtuous Spirits, shall at length obtain incorruptible, immortal, and Coelestial Bodies; yet those which they now wear, are not like to be made such: For it shall not be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, immortal, and Coelestial flesh, wherewith they shall be Cloathed in the Mansions of Eternity, but something else. Thus the Author of that anonymous Piece, the Account of <hi>Origen,</hi> &amp;c. delivers himself: <hi>That the Body we now have, is therefore Corruptible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is Flesh; and therefore if it put on incorruption and immortality, it must put off it self first, and cease to be Flesh,</hi> Page, 120. And again Pag. 125. <hi>If the Body of Flesh be a Mortal Body; if it be quickened, and made a living and immortal one, it must be made something else intrinsecally than what it was: But it being Flesh before, it must not be Flesh when it is inlivened too.</hi> So that by this device of a triple <hi>Congruity</hi> of Life, ingrafted in the <hi>Plastick</hi> of the Soul; the Resurrection of these <hi>identical</hi> Bodies, which we <hi>deposite</hi> at Death, is very fairly exploded. For if the Soul hath three such vital aptitudes, as before were named, and the <hi>Aethereal</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:54939:48"/> be the last that is invigorated; while it is so, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible that she should actuate any other Vehicle, than what is of an <hi>Aethereal</hi> Consistency. In Heaven there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no such thing as <hi>Glorified Flesh,</hi> nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently should our fleshly Bodies, ever be resusci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated in order to Glorification: Yet the word RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SURRECTION plainly implies thus much; that the same Bodies, which we leave behind us at our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence, shall rise again in their numerical Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: But then to illude this, we are told a fine Story; that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is a word of a <hi>lax and ambiguous signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> that it denotes <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> or a <hi>blessed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality;</hi> and according to this sense and reddition of it, we may have a true <hi>Resurrection,</hi> though our Bodies after our <hi>Analysis,</hi> sleep for ever in the Dust. But what a pitifull subterfuge, and helpless evasion is this? For if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, be properly <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> then whoever partake of the Resurrection (which all the Dead shall do) should participate of <hi>Immortality</hi> and <hi>Blessedness:</hi> And then what shall we make of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelists</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Resurrection of Condemnation</hi> spoken of St. <hi>John</hi> 5. 29? And that which farther marrs this Notion of <hi>Resurrection</hi> is, that our Church ties us to believe not the <hi>Resurrection</hi> simply, but the <hi>Resurrection of the Body</hi> (which surely we cannot Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the <hi>Blessedness</hi> and <hi>Immortality</hi> of the Soul) agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what our SAVIOUR professeth for his Will, St. <hi>John 6. 40. This is the Will of him that sent me, that every one which seeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have Everlasting Life; and I will raise him up at the last Day.</hi> And what will he raise up the <hi>Soul?</hi> That riseth into another Life, as soon as it departeth this: And therefore the <hi>Body</hi> must be the subject of the last days
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54939:48"/> Resurrection; whence by the way we may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice also, that <hi>Resurrection,</hi> and <hi>Everlasting Life,</hi> are not synonimous terms, but signifie two distinct things; for believers shall have <hi>Everlasting Life</hi> given them, and be <hi>Raised up</hi> besides.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Fourthly, it confines departed Souls, to very <hi>Comfortless</hi> and <hi>inconvenient Dwellings:</hi> For being released from their luggages of flesh, and toilsome burdens of Mortality (though they have done worthy things in this present State, and cordially served the Interests of JESUS) yet an immediate transition into Glory, must not be their recompence. No, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergefaction of their <hi>Aereal</hi> Congruity (which rouzeth it self, upon their first solution from these cadaverous Bodies) prevents their so early passage to the highest Regions; that, as this Hypothesis will have it, just upon their egression out of these terrene <hi>ergastula,</hi> catcheth hold on the <hi>proximate</hi> Air; and forming it into sutable Vehicles, forthwith claps them up therein, and secures their abode in vicinous places. And till they purifie themselves to such a degree, as to become fit for Union with <hi>Aethereal</hi> receptacles, they must be pent up in this inferiour World, and never think of emerging above the Terrestrial <hi>Atmosphere.</hi> Except it be a few of the <hi>Heroically</hi> Virtuous, and Men of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Goodness</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> (one in a Million perhaps) this is the Fate of <hi>Christians</hi> in general, at their dismission hence: They are removed but a little distance from the surface of the Earth, and must Hover about in the <hi>Circumfluent</hi> Air, till by their own indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, they can work themselves up aloft, and gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ascend into a purer Element. And methinks the Air is a very unmeet habitation, for Holy Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54939:49"/> both in respect of their Society, and other evils, that will their incommodate and molest them.</p>
               <p>First, their <hi>Company</hi> must needs be irksome and ingratefull: For the Air is the Devils Territory, the Seat of his Empire, and <hi>Metropolis</hi> of his Dominion: And therefore he is stiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Prince of the Power of the Air.</hi> There the supream <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hes. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note>
                  <hi>Magnifico,</hi> and Principal head of the <hi>Daemoniacal</hi> Body keeps his Court, as I may say, and sits upon his Throne, attended with his black and grisly Legions: And from thence he issues his Edicts, and dispenseth his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to the inferiour Ministers, and subordinate members of the Cursed <hi>Polity;</hi> and these again, have their under-Agents, which they constantly imploy in the menage of their Interests, and send abroad into the several Quarters of the World, to propagate and establish their <hi>Hellish</hi> Kingdom. So that we must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Aereal</hi> Regions to be fraught with Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of malignant <hi>Genii,</hi> that are continually passing, repassing, and flying about from one place to another, upon mischeivous Errands and Designs; and let the separate Souls of Good Men bestow themselves where they can; yet still so long as they are within the ambit of this fuliginous Air, they must alwayes be mingled with these lewd and malevolent Spirits, that will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually be intruding into their company. And though Providence has so hampered the malice, of this Rebel Rout, that they can by no means harm and injure them: Yet to be pestered and haunted with their evill presence, and to have them incessantly superintend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and inspecting their Actions; observing and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into their carriage; mocking and scoffing at their Religion, and the like; must needs be wondrous
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54939:49"/> burdensome and offensive to them: As it would be to the Righteous in this Life, to have their insolent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious and implacable Enemies, alwayes at their heels, to watch their behaviour, and take cognoscence of their doings, and to deride, and reprobate them upon all occasions.</p>
               <p>But besides, if they be cooped up, within the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosphere</hi> of the Earth, they must be obnoxious to many violencies and extremities, from Natural causes: sometimes they will be parched with intemperate <hi>Heat,</hi> sometimes almost frozen with excessive <hi>Cold,</hi> according to the Nature of the <hi>Climates</hi> they inhabit: Sometimes the Air is cloyed with smokie Fumes and Vapours: Sometimes filled with foggy Mists and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations: Sometimes constipated with Dense and Pitchy Clouds, which every foot discharge themselves in hideous Storms and Tempests; in flashes of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and claps of Thunder; in showrs of Rain and Hail, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if these in their rapid descent, chance to pervade their <hi>diaphanous</hi> Bodies, they must needs put them to intollerable torture. For their airy Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicles, being as intimately united to them, as our Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restrial ones are to us; for them to have their tender Bodies pierced and dilacerated, with boisterous showrs of Rain or Hail, will be all one in point of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery, as if we should have our Bodies, transfixed with Darts and Arrows, or shot through with little pellets of Lead or Iron: For look what execution these do upon our, the same they do upon their Vehicles.</p>
               <p>To avoid all these annoyances therefore, there is an expedient proposed, which I cannot but smile at, while I set it down; it is this: When they foresee Storms approaching, <hi>They might take shelter as other
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54939:50"/> living Creatures doe, in Houses, behind Walls, in Woods, Dales, Caverns, Rocks, and other obvious Places.</hi> A pretty conceit, and fit to make sport, for such as can think it worth the laughing at. As often as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens lowr, and scowl upon the Earth with an angry Countenance; the poor harbourless Souls, must pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently betake them all to their shifts: Some must shrig into dirty Stables; others must crowd into hollow Trees; others must sculk behind rotten Hedges; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers must nestle into Cony-burrows; and not dare to look out till the Storm be over, for fear they be rapt on the pate with Rain-drops, or have their <hi>Tiffany</hi> Vests blown off their backs, with the rufling Winds that threaten them: Others must sneak under the bellies of Cattle, to save themselves from the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and others must squeez through the Key-holes of Doors, to get into mens Houses, unless they durst venture down the Chimneys, or crawl up the Sink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holes. But not to be too impertinent: All the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions they can make for themselves, will not secure them from one inconvenience; the frequent returns of <hi>Night</hi> and <hi>Darkness:</hi> For once in twenty four hours, they must necessarily lose the Light and Influence of the Sun, and be inveloped in the conical shadow of the Earth; where unless it be the rays of the twinkling Starrs, or the languid beams of the pale-fac'd Moon (which in every <hi>Interlunium,</hi> or conjunction with the Sun, absconds her self) they have no light at all, to guide and cherish them; so that except they can see in the dark (which I presume they cannot, because then their <hi>visive</hi> Organs would be bright and radiant, and visible unto Men, as oft as they come near, or pass by them in the Night-time) their condition in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, is exceeding forlorn.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:54939:50"/>
               <p>Wherefore it is to be hoped, there is a better place of residence, prepared for Divine and Holy Souls, when they relinquish this, than the <hi>Air.</hi> And thus much, I think is easily colligible from the inspired Writings; in the 23. of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> we read of a flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Malefactor upon the Cross; and how he there commenced his repentance, just at his Death; so that he could not possibly arrive, at such an intrinsick and habitual Purity, before he was dissolved; as accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Hypothesis, is requisite to fit a Man, for an immediate ascent to the sublimest Regions, and the animation of an <hi>Aethereal</hi> Body: Yet our Blessed SAVIOUR there tells him, <hi>this day thou shalt be with me in Paradise:</hi> And that Paradise, is a place distinct from, and more excellent than the <hi>Air;</hi> may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the twelfth Chapter, of the second E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> there the <hi>Apostle</hi> informs us of a Man, caught up <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>into the Third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> which at the fourth Verse, he affirms to be <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise:</hi> So that <hi>Paradise</hi> must be the <hi>Third Heaven;</hi> that is the most lofty, and glorious Heaven of all: For it is denominated the <hi>Third Heaven,</hi> not <hi>ratione numeri,</hi> but <hi>dignitatis.</hi> As we say, that Man is <hi>thrice</hi> Happy, and <hi>thrice</hi> Blessed, whose condition is most prosperous and fortunate. So Paradise is said to be the <hi>Third Heaven,</hi> as being the most eminent, and <hi>superlative</hi> in Dignity and Excellence. And for the same reason it is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The most Heavenly Heavens. 1. Kings 8. 27. Psalm</hi> 148. 4. Now if this Penitent Theif, whose sanctity (by reason of the short space of time, intercurrent betwixt his Conversion and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) was very imperfect; was notwithstanding tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into <hi>Paradise,</hi> the <hi>Third Heaven,</hi> or <hi>Sedes Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:54939:51"/> upon the day of his <hi>Crucifixion:</hi> it is clear from hence, that not only the eminently, and heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Virtuous; but also the competently, if sincerely Religious, shall instantly upon their separation from the Body, be admitted into the most Blessed place, and perfect Felicity, that they can be capable of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the General Resurrection and Final Judgment. and if so, the <hi>Aereal</hi> Regions can be no permanent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of them after Death; nor have they such a Congruity in them, as does fatally Chain them to <hi>Airy</hi> Bodies, and so necessitate their abode in those places: If they had, our Church is guilty of vile un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableness, in that she does not supplicate for the Dead; who then are in a capacity of bettering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by virtuous endeavours, and our interpellations for them might help considerably towards their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Fifthly, it supposeth <hi>Men may Dye more than once:</hi> For as many as are forced into the other World, while their Terrestrial Congruity is in the height of invigoration, have no other remedy but to return hither, to get its <hi>Petulance</hi> quelled and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for so long as that continues strong and praedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant, the <hi>two</hi> other aptitudes are consopited and benummed; and therefore they cannot unite to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> or <hi>Aethereal</hi> Vehicles: Nor can they meet with any Terrestrial ones, in which to have the invigorated Principle castigated and debilitated, unless they be Born <hi>anew</hi> into this Life, and tread that Stage again, of which they were turned by a <hi>praemature exit:</hi> And till a fit opportunity invites them to re-enter it, they must rest, GOD knows where, in a state of silence and stupiditie. This one of the <hi>Champions</hi> of <hi>Praeex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:54939:51"/> delivers in plain terms, though in a sceptical <note place="margin">See Lux Orienta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis page 159. 160.</note> manner. <hi>Those that pass out of these Bodies, before the Terrestrial Congruity be spoil'd, weakened, and orderly unwound; must return into the state of inactivity: For the Plastick in them, is too highly awakened, to inactuate only an</hi> Aerial <hi>Body; and there being no other more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous, ready at hand for to enter; it must needs step back into its former state of insensibility, and there wait its turn, till befitting matter call it forth again, into Life and Action.</hi> All therefore at least that dye <hi>Infants,</hi> or by violence, their Earthly Congruities being not <hi>orderly unravel'd,</hi> and <hi>naturally dissolved</hi> and <hi>extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished;</hi> must back again into this World, time after time, till they hit upon mature and kindly expirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So that it seems <hi>Praeexistence</hi> and <hi>Transanimation</hi> go hand in hand: And the <hi>Samian</hi> Philosopher might not be so much mistaken, as some think he was, when he Sang of himself,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Trojani tempore Belli,</l>
                  <l>Panthoides Euphorbus eram.—</l>
               </q>
               <p>For the <hi>Trojan</hi> falling by the hand of <hi>Menelaus,</hi> and his dispossessed Soul being to seek for a Body, might haply wind it self into <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s: But surely then Interpreters are grosly out, in their Expositions of that speech of St. <hi>Pauls, It is appointed for men, once to Dye.</hi> And the Holy man was hardly aware of what he said, when he told his Friends. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>When the years of number are come, I shall go the way I shall not return.</hi> For, for ought he knew, he might have been cut off by a violent Death, and then a remigration hither would have been inevitable, or else this Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis is false: And were it true, it would give but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54939:52"/> small incouragement to <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> who lay down their Lives for Religion, and their Country, to think that as a recompence for their <hi>Magnanimous</hi> Pieties, they should be remanded back into this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable state, where perhaps they may dye in the same Circumstances again, and so lay a new train of infelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and entayl upon themselves a fresh calamity: Though I doubt not but it would render Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, exceeding venturous and daring in their nefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Atcheivements: And when they are apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and sentenc'd to suffer Capitally for their delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencies, it would chear them hugely, and make them jogg on merrily to their Execution, could they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they should only sleep a while after Death, and then recover their forfeited lives again: They would never scruple to Rob and to Kill; nor when they have done, dread the Ax or the Halter, did they think that nothing would follow, but a short intercision of life, and then a recuperation thereof, whereby they shall be inabled to resume the practice of their so gently mulcted Villanies, and to commit them over again, for the same Punishment.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In the last place, it makes the <hi>Glory of Heaven Transient</hi> and <hi>Amissible:</hi> For grant that Millions of Souls, reascend the <hi>Aethereal Elysium,</hi> and be installed anew in their <hi>Pristine</hi> beatitude; yet if <hi>Praeexistence</hi> speaks truth, they injoy no more now, than what they possessed long ago: And the same enticements, that tempted them to Sin, and betrayed them to misery at first, may do it a second time: For their condition being but the same it was, they are liable to be wrought upon by the same seducements, that before trepann'd them out of it. What though at present
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54939:52"/> the Plastick be tamed, and subjugated, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual Powers, be lively and vigorous? Yet in tract of time their sensitive faculties, that are now wound up and laid asleep, may revive and stirr afresh. When they have snored a while, and taken a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Nap, they may start out of their drowzie Fit, and becoming regnant as once they were, exile them from the Kingdom of the Blessed; 'tis like the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siful <hi>Platonist</hi> can delight himself in thinking, it shall be thus indeed: That the Rational and Plastick prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples shall act by turns through endless Vicissitudes, and rule <hi>alternatim</hi> in the Souls of Men to infinite Ages; the one still flagging and intermitting, when the other are most intended. But then the Great Question will be, how these Spirits, when they have deserted their happiness a second time, shall be able to regain it: For though the <hi>Son</hi> of GOD came down Heaven, and suffered once for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; yet to imagine that he should restore us again, by the same means; and as often as we fall, be Crucified for our recovery, would be a strange sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, and Contradictory to the Scripture.</p>
               <p>I could reckon up several other Absurdities, of the like Nature with the praecedent; but because I think those already specified, are more than enough to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that the Souls <hi>Heterogeneity,</hi> as above stated, is but an empty fiction; and not so much the Daughter of Truth, as the spurious Issue of a working Brain, and too parturient Phansie: I here take leave of this Objection, and proceed to the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:54939:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. Another <hi>Objection</hi> against <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> is <hi>our utter forgetting it in this Life.</hi> 2. A tripartite <hi>Evasion</hi> of the Objection propounded. 3. An Answer to the first Part. 4. An Answer to the Second Part. 5. An Answer to the Third Part of it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THat which in the Second place makes against <hi>Praeexistence</hi> is, that men upon Earth, <hi>are no whit Conscious to themselves of their living in a former State, nor of any thing therein represented to them:</hi> They remember not the Polity there erected and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished; nor the Laws there enacted and ordained; nor the Customs there used and observed: The scitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their Dwellings, the fashion of their Bodies, the nature of their Imployments, the manner of their Converse, and the quality of their Company, are all clearly out of their thoughts, nor can they for their hearts re-call them. And it seems incredible, that we should have injoyed a Blessed life, before our banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into this, where we had our Reason perfect, and our Faculties entire; our Spirits passive, and our Minds attentive (such as now they are) apt to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Scaenes</hi> of things, with ready notices, and deep resentments; and yet during our whole continuance here, be unable to recollect, and give the least ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of those commune occurrencies, which were
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54939:53"/> there most frequent and obvious to us. Had we ever inhabited the <hi>Aethereal</hi> Paradise, it would scarce have been forgotten; we should still have kept old Records of it, filed in our memories, which though they might have been much oblitterated and defaced, yet a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious search and examination of them, would discover something in them legible, as to the splendor and rare Felicities of the place.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But to take off this Objection it is Reply'd; that the Souls of Men in their descent from above, run through all those <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> that are most <hi>Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial</hi> and <hi>Pernicious</hi> unto <hi>Memory:</hi> And therefore 'tis no wonder they forget the Circumstances of the <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour</hi> Life; Nay, it would be a miracle if they should do otherwise.</p>
               <p>The things most fatal unto <hi>Memory,</hi> are observed to be Three. <hi>viz. Want of being reminded of a Matter. Desuetude, of thinking on it.</hi> And <hi>Extraordinary change in the Body.</hi> And of all these there is a joynt influence, and most eminent concurrence, to blurr and eat out the fair <hi>Ideaes,</hi> and memorial Characters of things, wherewith the Soul was stamped and impregnated, in an higher State: So that the Evasion contains three <hi>Creep-holes,</hi> out at which the Defenders of <hi>Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence</hi> would slink away, and slily convey themselves, to avoid the force of this Objection: But I think the <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> may easily be stopped, and their escape prevented.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For though the fore-cited accidents, which are confessedly diminutive and destructive of <hi>Memory,</hi> betide us in our Confinement to these fleshly Prisons; yet they are not sufficient to <hi>abolish</hi> our Remembrance of our ancient Condition, and to sink us down into a <hi>perfect Oblivion</hi> of all the passages and concerns thereof.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:54939:54"/>
               <p>First, the want of being reminded of them, is not enough to do it. There are many trifles in the World, which passing but once under our Observation, cleave fast unto our memories ever after; nor can we finally eject them, though we never meet with any like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currencies, to revoke them into our thoughts: And if our hasty notation of meer trivials, can cause so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent impressions; we must needs be more retentive and memorious, of those Objects that entertained our notices above. For their Glory and remarkableness, could not but draw us to solemn and studied <hi>animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions</hi> of them; and our long continuance amongst them, induce us often to reiterate the same, and so fix them Eternally in our minds. And indeed were these two particulars but well considered, what sumptuous and affecting Objects, adorn and beautisie the <hi>Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real</hi> Pallace: And what a tedious while we spent (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Platonick Hypothesis)</hi> in conversing with them, and musing on them, in viewing and re-viewing, and passionately admiring their splendor and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence; that we should forget them all, for lack of being <hi>Remembered</hi> of them, would seem impossible.</p>
               <p>But to come closer to the purpose; this first member of the Evasion, we want opportunities, and occasions to re-mind us of our <hi>Praeexistence</hi> is a pure pretence and palpable Figment. For imagine the supposal were true, that we were once loose from these uneasy Clods, that now afflict and burden us; and free to Range through the transparent Skies, in company with glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Angels: Admit we were once near Neighbours to the Sun, or dwelt in those Serene and Lightsome Countries, scituate beyond the Course of <hi>Saturn:</hi> Yet is the <hi>Scaene</hi> of <hi>that</hi> World, so different from <hi>this,</hi> that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54939:54"/> there is no resemblance at all between them? Can we here espy no <hi>Analogous</hi> Objects, to be fit <hi>Memorandums</hi> of those, with which we were there acquainted? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly here are some very consimilous to them (if not the same) the occursions of which, could not possibly miss of bringing them to our mind, if they were more than <hi>Phantastick</hi> and <hi>Imaginary:</hi> For grant we were once possessed of those <hi>Remote</hi> and <hi>Lucid</hi> habitations now mentioned; What in all likelihood, was our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment there? Was it not to contemplate and adore the <hi>Deity?</hi> To mark and study the Works of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation? To search and dive into the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? And to entertain one another with friendly Converse, and the profitable discourses of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Philosophy?</hi> And if these were our Excercises, in the <hi>Aethereal</hi> Tracts (as without dispute they were) to say we are here destitute, of apt <hi>Mementoes</hi> of our living there, would be a complaint unjust and frivolous: Because we are ingaged now, in the very same affairs, that we then attended; which undoubtedly would revive our Memory of them, if they had ever of old been familiar to us, and consequently of our Native Stations, wherein they were practised and often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated. And besides, if the Advocates of <hi>Praeexistence</hi> deceive us not, they have given us a just representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>place</hi> of our first abode; of the <hi>Bodies</hi> we wore, and of the <hi>Causes</hi> of our denudation of them. And these again are fair hints, and proper <hi>Items,</hi> to remind us of that place, and those <hi>Bodies,</hi> and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Contingencies, that deprived us of both: But since notwithstanding we are thus prompted to it, by vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of occasions, we can remember nothing of our <hi>Primitive</hi> Life; it is shrewdly to be suspected, that it,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54939:55"/> together with all the Circumstantiations thereof, is but Fictitious and Poetical.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor Secondly, will such a <hi>desuetude of thinking</hi> on the occurrencies of our <hi>Pristine</hi> State, as is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to seize us, in our descent from thence, be able to expunge and raise them out of our Remembrance: For it is not so much a bare dis-use of ruminating on things, that makes us forget them; as the Ebullition of fresh thoughts, and new Phantasms into our minds, which dash out all former Images, and representations there delineated. So that I am apt to believe, if a Man should fall into a profound sleep, and rest securely in the same, for many years together; yet at his evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilation, he would find his head fraught with lively <hi>Ideaes</hi> of such things, as he practised and observed before his repose. And the probability of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, is something warranted, by what hath happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Chronical</hi> Sleepers; who having lain for several Dayes, yea Weeks together, in the <hi>Arms</hi> of dull and heavy slumbers; at their expergefaction, have return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed instantly to those negotiations, they had in hand when they fell to rest, and have related exactly how they left them in every little Circumstance. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in descending from the upper World, we were intercepted (as they would make us believe) in a state of silence, and kept bound a while in the Chains of senselessness and inactivity, and an absolute cessation from thinking on all past concerns; yet there is no necessity from this, of our being overwhelmed with a <hi>total Oblivion</hi> of them: For we meeting in that state with no new <hi>series</hi> of cogitations, to disturb our minds, and discompose our memories, and crowd out those Notices, that before were fixed and recorded in them;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54939:55"/> they cannot be worn off, by a meer <hi>desuetude</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on them; especially considering they were deeply radicated, and that this <hi>desuetude</hi> was but short and transient: For though Lapsed Souls may (as the <hi>Platonists</hi> conceive) remain a long time in a stupid and inert condition; yet if the time of their lodging there (according to their own computation of it) be compared with their abode (as they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure it) in the spatious <hi>Aether,</hi> it will be very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable; scarce bearing the proportion of an hours sleep, to a dayes wakefulness: And as it is impossible that an hours sleep should blot all that business out of a Mans mind, which he dispatcht the whole day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: So it is improbable, that their lying dozed a while in the Air, should rob them of the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of those Transactions, about which they were imployed all the precedent part of their life: Or if the <hi>Aerial</hi> pernoctation, be not generally thus short, to all that drop into it; yet (which will serve our turn) it is acknowledged to be some: For as the Grand <hi>Propugnator</hi> of the Opinion confesseth, many by the procuration and assistance of the Spirit of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Dr. <hi>More his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. B. 3. C. 13. S.</hi> 10.</note>
                  <hi>may be fetcht from the purest Aethereal Regions, into a Humane Body, without serving any long Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiship in the intermediate Air:</hi> And consequently then, they should be able to bring some intelligence with them from the other World, they deserting it so late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and their <hi>desuetude</hi> of thinking on the affairs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being not very lasting.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To the third cause of forgetfulness above noted, I Answer; that though extraordinary <hi>Changes</hi> in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, be <hi>Labefactive</hi> of Memory; yet it does not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the Souls shifting of her Vehicle, should
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54939:56"/> throw all those objects out of her mind, the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative semblances of which, were there limmed out (as I may say) and pictured: For her egression out of one Body, and susception of another, fitly prepared to entertain her, is not so banefull unto Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as divers <hi>Mutations,</hi> to which this Earthly Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse is obnoxious: And though external Casualties, Diseases, and Senitude, work not so great a <hi>Change;</hi> yet they may be more disadvantageous to that faculty, than Death it self, which disseizeth us of our Body. This I know our Adversaries will not allow of: They tenaciously hold the contrary; that the dislodging of the Soul out of the Body, is more hurtfull to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, than those <hi>Changes</hi> which are superinduced to it: And hereupon they conclude, that if <hi>Changes</hi> wrought in the Body, by old Age, Sickness, or Disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, can root out the Memory of things in this life, as they have sometimes done; then much better may the Memory of <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> be done away by the Souls descent out of that state, because therein she undergoes a bigger <hi>Change,</hi> being forced to forsake the Vehicle, to which she was united; but I shall hardly be brought over to their perswasion; for though <hi>Changes</hi> in Body, may often imbecill, and sometimes utterly dispoil the Memory of things past; yet it is not necessary, that the Souls <hi>Changing</hi> of her Body, should therefore do so, because it is not so injurious to her Faculties: For the aforesaid evills, Violence, Aegritude, and Senility, may occasion a leisure of the Organs, or Distemperature of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, usefull and subservient to the Supream and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Functions; and thus Memory must needs be weakened and destroyed, till the inflicted mischief be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54939:56"/> repaired. And no wonder; for so even Reason it self, by accidental rudenesses and mischances, may be much debilitated, yea quite shattered and dissolved into brutishness and phrensie: But since it was not so serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by our Removal into these squallid Dungeons; from thence what I said even now, is fully verified: that if the supposed Passage of the Soul, out of a <hi>Praeexistent</hi> Body, were real and true, yet it could be nothing so prejudicial to her, as some <hi>Changes</hi> that are incident to this Body, during her residence here: If it were, not only our <hi>Memory,</hi> but <hi>Reason</hi> too, should have been calheired and lost, by our migrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of those Vehicles we formerly actuated, into these which we now inliven; but that still remaining sound and entire, and specificating our being by its eminence in us; it is manifest (I say) that the wrong and violence, sustained by <hi>Praeexistent</hi> Souls, in the <hi>Change</hi> of their habitations, is not so great as that which they suffer, from the tragical <hi>Disorders</hi> that frequently afflict their Earthly Tabernacles: And therefore though some decays and ruins, which fall out in those, may denude Men of Memory, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the frame and constitution of them; yet it does not follow, that their first immersion into them, should Cloud them with a black <hi>Oblivion</hi> of that life, which they are presumed to have spent on high: For then they sliding peaceably out of one Body into another, whose Organs were rightly framed, and Spirits duely tempered, their bare translocation could not be effective of such a thing; if it could, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate consequent of it would be monstrously ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd and impious; for thence it would instantly be inferred, that when People by Death are summoned
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54939:57"/> hence into unknown Regions provided for them; they shall quite be bereav'd of their <hi>Memory,</hi> and carry neither applause nor remordency of Conscience into the succeeding World; but if they have done well, their Benefactions shall be forgotten; and if they have done amiss, the sense of their Impieties shall be buried with them; and as for the never-dying Worm, so much talkt of by us, this one blow knocks out all his teeth, which are said to corrode the guilty: If the premised Doctrine be true, this is a Natural consequent of it; for it being granted, that the meer <hi>Translation</hi> of Souls, out of <hi>Aiery</hi> into <hi>Earthly</hi> Bodies, is enough to make them oblivious of all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of their <hi>Praeexistent</hi> life: We have reason to conclude, that their <hi>Return</hi> back out of these, into them again, will have the same influence and effects upon them, in reference to the passages of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent State. Were this deduction as true, as some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Tradition to be, which is the foundation of it; it would give Piety and Goodness such a mortal wound, that they would quickly bleed to Death: Then Virtue might meet with some store of Flatterers, but very few Friends; for it would proclaim Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but a sorry Scare-Crow, and an empty shadow; and pronounce Men ridiculous Fools, that should be affrighted with it, or allured by it: Supposing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we <hi>Praeexisted,</hi> we must either <hi>Remember</hi> something in this present life, of what we knew and acted, in that which is past; or else we must ground upon it, that we shall perfectly <hi>forget,</hi> that ever we were in this World, at our departure out of it; and who that is not a profest <hi>Atheist</hi> can do it? Thus for ought I perceive, the <hi>Objection</hi> yet stands unshaken,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54939:57"/> notwithstanding the foregoing Batteries made against it; and is so far from reeling into a ruinous heap, that it holds as firm as ever, and Triumphs in its own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnables.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. A Third <hi>Objection.</hi> 2. A Fourth <hi>Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IN the Third place it may be Objected against <hi>Praeexistence,</hi> that it makes it <hi>possible, nay necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that many Souls should enter into</hi> one <hi>Body:</hi> For before the Soul descends <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and comes to be joyned with a Terrestrial Vehicle, it supposeth both her <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is the <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>Intellectual Powers,</hi> and also her sensitive Faculties, to be Sunk into a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low condition of <hi>Lassitude</hi> and <hi>Debility;</hi> yea to be even quite consopited and stupified: So that now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her <hi>Plastick</hi> is exalted, and displays it self in a ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant energie, which puts her upon hunting (as I may say) after fitly prepared matter, into which to convey and incorporate her self; and at last being toucht with invisible reeks, and steems of <hi>Atoms,</hi> that Issue from the <hi>new-Conceptions</hi> of the Womb; and being delightfully wooed by these <hi>Histerical Effluviaes,</hi> she still moves nearer and nearer towards the source out of which they fly, and never rests, till her Bridal with the Body be Consummated, and she be wholly absorpt of that slimy Spirituous <hi>Mass,</hi> whence flowed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54939:58"/> those gratefull and attractive emissions. But now this <hi>Plastick</hi> Principle, which rules the <hi>Stupid</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptive</hi> Souls, being <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>sensless,</hi> what hinders but <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>three,</hi> or <hi>more</hi> of them, following the conduct of its heedless <hi>impetus,</hi> may be hurried down together, and jumbled into the same lump of <hi>Spumous</hi> Matter, and so joyntly exercising their efformative Power upon it, shape it into a <hi>Bipartite,</hi> or <hi>Tripartite</hi> Monster, according to the number of the <hi>Inmates?</hi> Nay, the thing is not only possible, but thus methinks it must <hi>inevitably</hi> happen in most Generations: For the expirations of life in the Air, being far more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous than the Bodily preparations upon Earth, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most every little Corner of it, will be full of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> Spirits: And the <hi>Ambient</hi> Air being thus throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, every <hi>Atmosphere</hi> arising from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Generation, must include a good Company: And they all Lying within the compass of its activity, why should not the same influence that Charms down <hi>one,</hi> to Unite to those Rudiments of life, tempt the <hi>rest</hi> to do so too, (they in every respect being as fit and easy to be wrought upon) and so all Co-enter into one Body? Nor will the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which is said to have a great hand in Conducting Souls, to their Earthly Prisons, afford any help at all, at this dead lift: For that is a substance without <hi>Sense and Animadversion too,</hi> and so more like to promote the Error we now discourse of, than any way to prevent it; though truly to speak my own thoughts, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is no such Creature in Being: And this very Clause of her Definition, <hi>that she is a Substance without Sense and Animadversion,</hi> seems to prove as much, it being little less in my apprehension, than
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54939:58"/> a Contradiction; as much as to say, a <hi>material Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> For there, the <hi>want of Sense</hi> and <hi>Animadversion,</hi> the immediate and inseparable property of <hi>Matter,</hi> is ascribed to the Soul of the World; which argues plainly she is no <hi>Spirit;</hi> for a <hi>Spirit</hi> is opposite to Matter in <hi>Essence,</hi> and therefore must be the like, in all its <hi>Essential</hi> and immediate <hi>Attributes;</hi> which the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> is not, if she be rightly defined, as before was noted, to be <hi>devoid of Sense and Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Lastly, <hi>Praeexistence</hi> will be excepted against, in that <hi>it supposeth the rest of the Planets, to be Peopled with Mankind:</hi> For if the whole <hi>Caetus</hi> of <hi>Praeex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istent</hi> Souls, did Originally Cohabit in those tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Regions, that are stretched out beyond the height of <hi>Saturn;</hi> it cannnot be that their Apostacy should transmit them all directly to this little Globe of Earth, and that they should miss of the other <hi>Planets</hi> in the way, whose bulks are Vaster, and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuations nearer to the Happy place of their first a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode: And yet if they chanced to light into any of them, what will be their Fortune there? Shall they ever be redeemed, and put in a Capacity of recovering their forfeited Blessedness, or not? To say they shall not, would be to scandalize Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and to tax GOD who declares himself, to be no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with a base Partiality, in that he paid a price for our Ransom, but grudges to do the like for them, who are every way as deserving as our selves. Redeemed therefore they must be; but how? He cannot <hi>deposite</hi> the same <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for them, that he did for us; <hi>For</hi> CHRIST <hi>dyeth no more: Death hath no more Dominion over</hi> HIM; nor can
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54939:59"/> another so precious be thought on; nor can one of less value serve the turn: So that what will become of them I know not; only they will be very miserable, or else I Conclude (which is most likely) that <hi>there is no PRAEEXISTENCE.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>